<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<preface>


AN



ARABIC-ENGLISH
LEXICON






AN



ARABIC-ENGLISH

LEXICON



BY
EDWARD WILLIAM LANE



IN EIGHT PARTS
PART 1



LIBRAIRIE DU LIBAN

Riad el - Solh Square

BEIRUT - LEBANON

19 6 8






&lt; oiif jLifll j £-1^ « l^VUi-i viJu; i^isl^j &lt;1uji jiU^ii

' ' 'It- - _, .-



PUBLISHER'S NOTE

Edward William Lane's ARABIC -ENGLISH LEXICON
Book I contains all the classical words, their derivatives,
and their usages. It appears in eight separate volumes
and took the author more than thirty years to compile.

Book II, which Dr. Lane contemplated and which was
to contain rare words and explanations, was incomplete
at the time of his death in 1876 and therefore never
appeared.

In describing Lane's Lexicon, Dr. G. P. Badger wrote.
" This marvellous work in its fullness and richness, its
deep research, correctness and simplicity of arrangement
far transcends the Lexicon of any language ever pre-
sented to the world. »



Printed in Lebanon by OFFSET CONROGRAVURfc



Y -*■ S




AN



AEABIC-ENGLISH

LEXICON,

DERIVED FROM THE BEST AND THE MOST COPIOUS EASTERN SOURCES;

COMPRISING A VERY LARGE COLLECTION

OF WORDS AND SIGNIFICATIONS OMITTED IN THE KAMOOS,

WITH SUPPLEMENTS TO ITS ABRIDGED AND DEFECTIVE EXPLANATIONS,

AMPLE GRAMMATICAL AND CRITICAL COMMENTS,

AND EXAMPLES IN PROSE AND VERSE:

COMPOSED BY MEANS OE THE MUNIFICENCE OF THE MOST NOBLE

ALGERNON,
DUKE OF NORTHUMBERLAND, K.G.,

ETC. ETC. ETC.,

AND THE BOUNTY OF

THE BRITISH GOVERNMENT:
BY BDWAHD WILLIAM LANE.



IN TWO BOOKS:

THE FIRST CONTAINING ALL THE CLASSICAL WORDS AND SIGNIFICATIONS COMMONLY KNOWN

TO THE LEARNED AMONG THE ARABS :
THE SECOND, THOSE THAT ARE OF RARE OCCURRENCE AND NOT COMMONLY KNOWN.

BOOK I.— PART 1.



WILLIAMS AND NORGATE,

14, HENRIETTA STREET, COVENT GARDEN, LONDON;

AND 20, SOUTH FREDERICK STREET, EDINBURGH.

1863.






TO

THE MOST NOBLE

ALGERNON,
DUO OF NORTHUMBERLAND, K.G.,

ETC. ETC. ETC.,

THE ORIGINATOR OF THIS WOKK,
AND ITS CONSTANT AND MAIN SUPPORTER,
THE AUTHOR DEDICATES IT.



WITH

PROFOUND RESPECT

AND

GRATITUDE.



PREFACE.



In the year 1842, a most generous offer made to me by the present Duke of Northumberland (then Lord Prudhoe) enabled me
to undertake the composition of this work; and to His Grace's princely aid I have ever since been mainly indebted for
the means of accomplishing the project thus originated.

The object proposed was not to do in English little more than what Golius and others had already done in Latin, by
translating and composing from a few Arabic lexicons of the class of epitomes or abstracts or manuals; but to draw chiefly
from the most copious Eastern sources; one of which, comprising in about one seventh part of its contents the whole of the
celebrated Kiiinoos, I knew to exist in Cairo. There, also, I had reason to believe that I might find other sources unknown in
Europe, and obtain more aid ill the prosecution of my design than I could elsewhere; and thither, therefore, I betook myself
for this purpose.

On my arrival at Cairo, I first had recourse, for help in making my preparations, to an accomplished Arabic Scholar,
the late M. Fulgencc Fresnel, with whom, during a former residence in Egypt, I had contracted an intimate friendship.
Previously informed by mc of my project, he had tested the qualifications of several learned natives for the task of assisting
me in collecting, transcribing, and collating, the materials from which my lexicon was to be composed ; and he recommended
to me, as tbc person whom he esteemed the most fit, the shcykh Ibrahcem (surnamed 'Abd-el-Ghaffar) Ed-Dasookec. To have
engaged as my coadjutor ft shcykh respected for his character and learning, and to have been disappointed in him, and obliged
to dismiss him, might have made him my enemy, and enabled and induced him to baffle my scheme; but my experience led
mc to believe that a person better qualified for the services that I required of him, than the sheykh Ibrahcem Ed-Dasookce,
could not have been found by mc in Cairo; and I had no occasion to employ any other assistant, except, occasionally,
transcribers, under his supervision.

The assistance that I received from my friend M. Fresnel was not limited to the favour mentioned above. With a
generosity rarely equalled, he insisted upon transferring to mc the most valuable of his Arabic manuscripts, to remain with me
during the whole period of the composition of my lexicon, and in case of his death during that period to become my absolute
property. Most deeply do 1 deplore his not having lived to see how greatly those precious manuscripts have contributed to
the accuracy and value of my work, and to have them restored to him. They consist of two copies of the Sihah and a copy
of the Kiimoos. One of the copies of the former lexicon is a manuscript of extraordinary excellence : it was finished in the
year of the Flight 676 (a.d. 1277) ; and forms a large quarto-volume. The other copy of the same lexicon is in three
volumes : the second volume surpasses in accuracy every other copy of the same work that I have seen, and is enriched with
numerous important extracts, in its margins, from the celebrated Annotations of Ibn-Barree and El-Bustee: the first volume
is similarly enriched, and little inferior to the second in accuracy : the third is of the ordinary quality. The copy of the
Kamoos, which is written in a very small and compact hand, and forms a single octavo- volume, I believe to be unique : it
contains, in its margins, (with other annotations and with various readings,) copious extracts from the great work which is
the main source of my own lexicon; and its text, of which the transcription was finished in the year of the Flight 1120
(a.d. 1708-9), has been carefully collated. These valuable acquisitions I made almost immediately after my arrival at Cairo.

It was indispensable, I believe, to the success of my undertaking, that I should most carefully avoid whatever might
draw down disrespect from the 'Ulama of Cairo, or others of the Muslim inhabitants, either upon myself or upon the sheykh
Bk. I.






vi PREFACE.

who was to assist me in procuring the chief materials for the composition of my work. For it was only by his means that I
could reasonably hope to obtain the use of manuscripts in the libraries of mosques ; that is, by his borrowing those manuscripts
as though for his own use: and one of the librarians showed himself to be desirous of urging any pre.text in order to refuse the
loan of the work that I most needed. I therefore made my place of residence" to be as far as I could from the quarters
frequented by Franks, and conformed with such of the general usages of the Muslims as did not involve a profession of
their religion. But my precautions did not suffice to secure me from every difficulty. Even the Viceroy, Mohammad 'Alee
Pasha, though almost an absolute prince, could not enable me to overcome them. Hearing of my project, I know not how,
he spontaneously informed me, by his Prime Minister, that he was desirous of showing his respect for my Patron by rendering
me any assistance within his power. I replied that his Highness would very greatly aid me by granting me authority to
demand the loan of certain manuscripts in the libraries of mosques. But it was feared that the wardens of the mosques would
in this case urge the necessity of an order from the Sultan, or abstract considerable portions from those manuscripts and so
defeat my plan. I could therefore only endeavour to obtain, according to the usual custom, through the shcykh my assistant,
a small portion at a time of each of the required manuscripts: and even this I was unable to do until after the lapse of some
weeks. In the mean time, however, I had the good fortune to acquire a large folio-volume, consisting of nearly the whole of
the first tenth portion, of a copy of the great work to which I have alluded before as comprising in about one seventh part of
its contents the whole of the celebrated Kamoos. This work, entitled "Taj cl-'Aroos" (^-j^ill --U), a compilation from the best
and most copious Arabic lexicons, in the form of a running commentary on the Kamoos, with necessary critical and other
illustrations, original, and selected from various authors of high repute, fully justified my expectation. I found, from the
portion before me, that it would of itself alone suffice to supply the means of composing an Arabic lexicon far more accurate
and perspicuous, and incomparably more copious, than any hitherto published in Europe. But I should not have been satisfied
with making use of it for such a purpose without being able to refer to several of the most important of the works from which

it was compiled.

-

Of these works, and others particularly deserving of notice, as well as of the Taj cl-'Aroos itself, and of the principles of
Arabic lexicology, I must now endeavour to give a brief account. In doing this, I shall frequently have occasion to cite the
"Muzhir" of Es-Suyootee, a compilation of the utmost value to students in general, and more especially to lexicographers, of the
Arabic language. Its author died in the year of the Flight 911, a date to be borne in mind in perusing my extracts from it.
I possess a most excellent copy of it, (written by a learned man, the shcykh Nasr El-Hoorccncc, with the exception of a
portion which, while he was suffering from an attack of ophthalmia, was written for him by one of his disciples,) transcribed
from the best that is known to exist in Cairo, (namely, that of Es-Seja'ec, in the library of the great mosque El-Azhar,) and
enriched with copious marginal notes.

What is called the classical language of Arabia, often termed by the Arabs " the language of Ma'add," and " the
language of Mudar," is a compound of many sister-dialects, very little differing among themselves, which were spoken
throughout nearly the whole of the Peninsula before the religion of Mohammad incited the nation to spread its conquering
armies over foreign countries. Before that period, feuds among the tribes, throughout the whole extent of their territory, had
prevented the blending of their dialects into one uniform language; but this effect of disunion was counteracted in a great
measure by the institution of the sacred months, in which all acts of hostility were most strictly interdicted, and by the annual
pilgrimage, which had obtained from time immemorial, and the yearly fair held at 'Ok&amp;dh, at which the poets of various
tribes, during a period of about a century before the birth of Mohammad, or perhaps during a somewhat longer period,
contended for the meed of general admiration.*



• Respecting this fair, sec sonic extracts from the first of M. Frcsnel's " Lettrcs sur 1'IIistoirc des Arabcs avant I'lslamisme" in Note 18 to the
first chapter of my Translation of the Thousand and One Nights.






PREFACE. vii

" Katiideh says that the tribe of Kureysh used to cull what -was most excellent in the dialects of the Arabs, so that their
dialect became the most excellent of all." (Taj el-'Aroos, in article ,_&gt;;*: and the like is said in the 9th Section of the Muzhir.)
This assertion, however, is not altogether correct : for many of the children of the tribe of Kureysh, in the time of Mohammad,
were sent into the desert to be there nursed in order to their acquiring the utmost chasteness of speech. Mohammad himself
was sent to be nursed among the tribe of Saad Ibn-Bekr Ibn-Hawazin, descendants of Mudar, but not in the line of Kureysh :
and he is said to have urged the facts of his being of Kureysh and having grown up among the tribe of Saad as the grounds of
his claim to be tlic most chaste in speech of the Arabs. It is evident, therefore, that Kureysh, in his time, were less chaste
in spcecli than some other tribes ; though the truth of this asserted saying of his rests, I believe, only on the authority of a
Saadcc, who may have forged it in order to raise the reputation of his own tribe for purity of speech. From distant tribes,
Kureysh probably borrowed little. The dialect of Himycr, confined mainly to El- Yemen, and allied much more to the Ethiopic and
the Hebrew than to the language of Ma'add, contributed to this last language little more than a small proportion of words. For
our knowledge of it, which is very scanty, we are chiefly indebted to the researches of M. Fresnel, who discovered a surviving
idiom of it, spoken chiefly in the district of Mahreh, between Iladramowt and 'Oman : hence it has been termed " Mahrce ;"
and from the name of the tribe who speak it, M. Fresnel gave it the appellation of "Ehhkili," or "Ehkili." The author of
the " Misbah" (El-Fciyoomcc) says, in article ^,, " The language of the people of Mahreh, which is a district of 'Oman, is quick,
and scarcely, or not at all, intelligible [to other Arabs], and is of the ancient Ilimyerce."

The language of Ma'add was characterized by its highest degree of perfection, copiousness, and uniformity, in the time
of Mohammad; but it soon after declined, and at length lost almost all that constituted its superiority over the other branches
of the Semitic stock in the states in which these arc known to us. It is evident that all the Semitic languages diverged from
one form of speech : and the known history of the Arabic is sufficient, I think, to show that the mixture of the several
bianchrs of the Shcmites, in different degrees, with different foreign races, was the main cause, if not of the divergence, at least
of the decay, of their languages, as exemplified by the Biblical Hebrew and Chaldee, and the Christian Syriac. That their
divergence also was thus mainly caused, we cannot prove; but that this was the case I do not doubt, judging from the
differences in their vocabularies, more especially from the differences of this kind in the Hebrew and Phoenician from the other
Semitic languages. The existence of at least one language widely differing from the Semitic very long before the age of Moses
is proved by the remains of the ancient Egyptian, from the time of the Pyramids; a language predominantly Semitic in its
grammar, but predominantly Non-Semitic in its vocabulary; and evidently a compound of two heterogeneous forms of speech.
The opinion, common among the learned of the Arabs, that the Arabic is the offspring of the Syriac, apparently suggested by-
a comparison of their vocabularies and by false notions of development, is simply absurd, unless by "the Syriac" we
understand a lost language very different from that which is known to us by this appellation.* Every language without a
written literature tends to decay more than to development by reason of foreign influences ; and the history of the Arabic
exhibits an instance of decay remarkably rapid, and extraordinary in degree. An immediate consequence of the foreign
conquests achieved by the Arabs under Mohammad's first four successors was an extensive corruption of their language: for
the nations that they subdued were naturally obliged to adopt in a great measure the speech of the conquerors, a speech which
few persons have ever acquired in such a degree as to be secure from the commission of frequent errors in grammar without
learning it from infancy. These nations, therefore, and the Arabs dwelling among them, concurred in forming a simplified
dialect, chiefly by neglecting to observe those inflections and grammatical rules which constitute the greatest difficulty of the
classical Arabic: in the latter half of the first century of the Flight, this simplified dialect became generally spoken in the
foreign towns and villages inhabited by the Arabs ; and it gradually became the general language throughout the deserts, as
well as the towns and villages, of Arabia itself. That such a change took place, in the language of the Arabs inhabiting
foreign towns and villages, at this period, is shown by several anecdotes interspersed in Arabic works, and amply confirmed in



• Many among the Jews, the Syrians, and the Fathers of the Christian Church, held that the Aramaic or the Syriac was the language of Adam.



viii PREFACE.

the older Arabic lexicons and other lexicological works by instances of the necessity of appeals to contemporary Arabs of the
desert, respecting points of grammar, by learned men whose parents lived in the first century of the Flight The celebrated
lexicologist El-Asma'ee, who was born in the year of the Flight 123, and lived to the age of 92 or 93, was not a sound
grammarian. (See De Sacy's " Anthol. Gr. Ar." p. 49 of the Arabic text.) And even Seebaweyh, who was contemporary,
during the whole of his comparatively short life, with El-Asma'ee, appears to have erred in grammar. (See p. 133 of the
present work.) Ibn-Seedch says, in the " Mohkam," in art. fc^,, (voce ££-,) that El-Asma'ee was not a grammarian : and in
art. ^jZ, (voce 4&gt;aP&gt; as P^- °^ Vj^&gt;) ^ e remarks that Ibn-El-Aarabee (who calls ^jl&gt; pi. of 4&gt;ji») was ignorant of grammar.
In short, not a single instance is known of any one's having acquired a perfect knowledge of the grammar of the classical
Arabic otherwise than by being brought up among Arabs who retained that language uncorrupted. The Khaleefeh El-Weleed
(who reigned near the close of the first century of the Flight), the son of 'Abd-El-Melik, spoke so corrupt a dialect that he
often could not make himself understood by the Arabs of the desert. A ridiculous instance of the mistakes occasioned by
his use of the simplified language which is now current is related by Abul-Fida. The rapid progress of the corruption of
the language among the learned is the more remarkable when it is considered that many of these, in the first and second
centuries of the Flight, were very long-lived: for in a list of the most celebrated Arabic lexicologists and grammarians,
in the 48th Section of the Muzhir, the first five whose lengths of life are defined attained the following ages : 92, 74, 93, 96
or 97 or 98 or 99, and 92 or 93 : the first of these (Yoonus) was born in the year 90 of the Flight; and the last, in the year
123; this being El-Asma'ee. This series of five is broken only by one, whose length of life is not known. In some
few spots, the language of Ma'add long lingered ; and it may perhaps even survive to the present day ; as appears from the
following curious statement in the Kamoos (article j£&amp;): "'Akadis a certain mountain, near Zebeed, [a well-known city in
the western seaboard of El- Yemen,] the inhabitants of which retain the chaste language:" to which is added in the Tilj
el-'Aroos, that they retain this language "to the present time [the middle of the eighteenth century]: and the stranger remains
not with them more than three nights, [the period prescribed by the law for the entertainment of a stranger,] by reason of
[their] fear for [the corruption of] their language." But instances of the corruption of the classical Arabic are related (in the
44th Section of the Muzhir) as having occurred even in the life-time of Mohammad.

Such being the case, it became a matter of the highest importance to the Arabs to preserve the knowledge of that
speech which had thus become obsolescent, and to draw a distinct line between the classical and post-classical languages.
For the former language was that of the Kur-an and of the Traditions of Mohammad, the sources of their religious, moral,
civil, criminal, and political code: and they possessed, in that language, preserved by oral tradition, — for the art of writing,
in Arabia, had been almost exclusively confined to Christians and Jews, — a large collection of poetry, consisting of odes and
shorter pieces, which they esteemed almost as much for its intrinsic merits as for its value in illustrating their law. Hence
the vast collection of lexicons and lexicological works composed by Arabs, and by Muslims naturalized among the Arabs;
which compositions, but for the rapid corruption of the language, would never have been undertaken. In the aggregate of
these works, with all the strictness that is observed in legal proceedings, as will presently be shown, the utmost care and
research have been employed to embody everything that could be preserved or recovered of the classical language; the result
being a collection of such authority, such exactness, and such copiousness, as we do not find to have been approached in the
case of any other language after its corruption or decay.

The classical language they called, by reason of its incomparable excellence, * el-loghah," or " the language :" and the
line between this and the post-classical was easily drawn, on account of the almost sudden commencement, and rapid progress,
of the corruption. It was decided by common consent, that no poet, nor any other person, should be taken as an absolute and
unquestionable authority with respect to the words or their significations, the grammar, or the prosody, of the classical
language, unless he were one who had died before the promulgation of El- Islam, or who had lived partly before and partly
after that event; or, as they term it, unless he were a "Jahilee" or a "Mukhadram," or (as some pronounce it) "Mukhadrim,"






PREFACE.

or "Muhadram," or "Muhadrim." A poet of the class next after the Mukhadrams is termed an "Isldmee:" and as the
corruption of the language had become considerable in his time, even among those who aimed at chasteness of speech, he is not
cited as an authority absolutely and unquestionably like the two preceding classes. A poet of the next class, which is the hit,
is termed a "Muwelled:" he is absolutely postal assical ; and is cited as an unquestionable authority with respect only to the
rhetorical sciences. The commencement of the period of the Muwelleds is not distinctly stated: but it must have preceded
the middle of the second century of the Flight ; for the classical age may be correctly denned as having nearly ended
with the first century, when very few persons born before the establishment of El-Islam through Arabia were living. Thus
the best of the Islamee poets may be regarded, and are generally regarded, as holding classical rank, though not as being
absolute authorities with respect to the words and the significations, the grammar, and the prosody, of the classical language.
The highest of all authorities, however, on such points, prosody of course excepted, is held by the Arabs to be the Kur-dn.
The Traditions of Mohammad are also generally held to be absolute authorities with respect to everything relating to the prose
of the classical language; but they are excluded by some from the class of absolute authorities, because traditions may be
corrupted in language, and interpolated, and even forged. Women are often cited as authorities of equal rank with men : and
in like manner, slaves reared among the Arabs of classical times are cited as authorities equally With such Arabs. (See the
word **&amp; in the present work; and see also ^ and^^ and ^*lt and Jfc.)

The poetry of the Jdhilees and Mukhadrams consists, first, of odes (termed j»2&gt; plural of i*J), which were regarded
as complete poems, and which were all designed to be chanted or sung: secondly, of shorter compositions, termed pieces
(-Ll plural of a^5); many of which were also designed to be chanted or sung: and thirdly, of couplets, or single verses. In
thefirst of these classes are usually included all poems of more than fifteen verses : but few odes consist of much less than fifty
verses or much more than a hundred. Of such poems, none has been transmitted, and none is believed to have existed, of an
age more than a few generations (probably not more than three or four or five) anterior to that of Mohammad. It is said in
the 49th Section of the Muzhir, on the authority of Mohammad Ibn-Seldm El-Jumahee, that "the pristine Arabs had no
poetry except the few verses which a man would utter in his need: and odes (kaseedehs) were composed, and poetry made
long only [for the first time] in the age of 'Abd-El-Muttalib [Mohammad's grandfather], or Hashim Ibn-'Abd-Mendf [his
great-grandfather]." And shortly after, in the same Section of that work, it is said, on the same authority, that "the first
who composed poems of this kind was El-Muhelhil Ibn-Rabee'ah Et-Teghlibee, on the subject of the slaughter of his brother
Kuleyb •" - he was maternal uncle of Imra-el-Keys* Ibn-Hojr El-Kindee." - Or, according to 'Omar Ibn-Shebbeh, each tribe
claimed priority for its own poet; and not merely as the author of two or three verses, for such they called not a poem: the
Yemdnees claimed for Imra-el-Keys; and Benoo-Asad, for 'Abeed Ibn-El-Abras ; and Teghlib, for [E1-] Muhelhil; and Bekr,
for 'Amr Ibn-Ramee-ah and El-Murakkish El-Akbar; and Iydd, for Aboo-Du-dd: and some assert that El-Afwah El-Azdee
was older than 'these, and was the first who composed kaseedehs: but these for whom priority in poetry was claimed were
nearly contemporary; the oldest of them probably not preceding the Flight by a hundred years, or thereabout. Thaalab says,
in his 'Amdlee/ El-Asmaee says that the first of the poets of whom is related a poem extending to thirty verses is [E1-]
Muhelhil: then, Dhu-eyb Ibn-Kaab Ibn-'Amr Ibn-Temeem Ibn-Damreh, a man of Benoo-Kindneh ; and El-Adbat Ibn-Kureya:
and he says, Between these and El-Isldm was four hundred years: and Imra-el-Keys was long after these." But this is
inconsistent with the assertion of Ibn-Seldm mentioned above, made also by En-Nawawee in his " Tahdheeb el-Asma," p. 163,
that El-Muhelhil was maternal uncle of Imra-el-Keys: and as the majority refer El-Muhelhil to a period of about a century
before the Flight, we have a double reason for holding this period (not that of four hundred years) to be the more probably



• This name is generally pronounced thus, or " Imr-el-$eys," by the
learned among the Arabs in the present day; for most of them regard it as
pedantic to pronounce proper names in the classical manner. The classical
pronunciation is " Imraii-l-^eys" and » Imruu-l-^eys" and Imru-1-



Keys ;" in the last instance without hemzeh, because (as is said ;n the
Tahdheeb and the Taj el-'Aroos on the authority of El-Kisa-ee and El-
Farra) this letter is often dropped.



X PREFACE.

correct. According to Ibn-Kuteybch, the time of Imra-cl-Keys was forty years before that of Mohammad ; as is stated in the
Calcutta edition of the Mo'allakat. M. Fresnel contends that the honour commonly ascribed to El-Muhelhil is due to Zuhcyr
Ibn-Jemlb El-Kclbee, of whose poetry at least seventy-nine verses have been preserved, fragments of different poems, including
a piece of fifteen verses, of which the first hemistich of the first verse rhymes with the second hemistich, according to rule
But this Zuheyr, during a portion of his life, is related to have been contemporary with El-JfuheM. In a fragment ascribed
to him, he represents himself (if the fragment be genuine) to have lived two hundred years: and one tradition assigns to him
a life of two hundred and fifty years ; another, four hundred years ; and another, four hundred and fifty years!*— Upon the
whole, then, it seems that wo may with probability refer the first kasccdeh to a period within a century and a half, at the
utmost, before the Flight.

Mohammad said, on being asked, " Who is the best of the poets 1" " Imra-el-Keys will be the leader of the poets to

Hell." And in the general estimation of the Arabs, he is the most excellent of all their poets. II is Mo'allakah is most

especially admired by them. Of the pagan and unbelieving poets who flourished before and during the time of Mohammad, El-

Bcydawce sarcastically remarks (on chap. xxvi. verses 224 and 225 of the Kur-j'm, in which, and in the verse that next follows,

they arc censured as seducers, bewildered by amorous desire, and vain boasters,) " Most of their themes are unreal fancies, and

their words chiefly relate to the description of the charms of women under covert, and amorous dalliance, and false arrogations

or professions, and the rending of reputations, and the impugning of the legitimacy of parentages, and false threatening, and

vain boasting, and the praise of such as do not deserve it, with extravagance therein." The like is also said in the Kcshsluif,

(on the same passage of the Kur-iln,) and in too large a degree we must admit it to be just ; but it is very f:ir from being

unexceptionable. The classical poetry is predominantly objective, sensuous, and passionate ; witli little imagination, or fancy,

except in relation to phantoms, or spectres, and to jinn, or genii, and other fabulous beings ; and much less artificial than

most of the later poetry, many of the authors of which, lacking the rude spirit of the Bedawecs, aimed chiefly at mere

elegancies of diction, and plays upon words. Generally speaking, in the chissical poetry, the descriptions of nature, of the lifr

of the desert, of night-journeyings and day-journcyings, with their various incidents, of hunting, and stalking, and lurking for

game, of the tending of camels, of the gathering of wild honey, and similar occupations, are most admirable. And very curious

and interesting, as will be shown by many citations in the present work, arc its frequent notices (mostly by early Muslim

poets) of the- superstitions that characterized, in the pagan times, the religion most generally prevailing throughout Arabia ;

in which, with the belief in a Supreme Deity, with strange notions of a future state, and with angdolatry, sistrolatry, and

idolatry, was combined the lowest kind of fetishism, chiefly the worship of rocks and stones and trees, probably learned from

Negroes, of whom the Arabs have always had great numbers as slaves, and with whom they have largely intermixed.

Sententious language consisting of parallel clauses, like that of the so-called " poetical books" of the Bible, was probably often

employed by tho Arabs of every age. It seems to be almost natural to their race when excited to eloquence. But the

addition of rhyme in this style of language appears to have become common in the later times. Mohammad Ibn-Et-Teiyib

El-FAsee says (in article ^.Ua. of his Annotations on the Knmoos) that the oration termed *!&amp;*., in the Pagan and the early

Muslim ages, was, in most instances, not in rhyming prose. The remains of classical prose are often used as authorities ; but

being more liable to corruption, they are regarded as less worthy of reliance than the poetry .t



• See the first nnd second and third of M. FrcsneFs " Lettrcs sur
l'Histoirc des Arabcs avant l'lslamisme:" the second and third in the
" Journal Asiatique," 3rd Series, vols. 3 and 5.

t Thoso who desire to pursue the study of the history of the classical
Arabic beyond tho limits to which I have here confined my remarks,
together with that of its sister-languages, will find much learned and
valuable information in M. Kenan's " Histoire Generate et Systeme
Compare des Langues Semitiques;" though his scepticism in relation to



questions merely philological (as well as to sacred mutters) is often, iu
my opinion, ill-grounded and unreasonable. I must particularly remark
upon his erroneous assertion that the poems of the U"c anterior to El-
Islam make no allusion to the ancient religions of Arabia, and hence
appear to have been expurgated by Muslims, so as to efface all traces of
paganism. Many of such allusions, by pagan poets, might be adduced
from lexicons, grammars, and scholia ; and some examples of them will
be found in the present work, in articles j^j and jc- and i« Sec. ; tho

[first












PREFACE.



XI



Such are the principal original sources from which the Arabic lexicons and lexicological works have been derived.
Another source consisted of phrases and single words transmitted from the Arabs of classical times, or from those later Arabs
of the desert who were believed (though they were not regarded as unquestionable authorities) to have retained the pure
language of their ancestors. The earlier of these are often called, by the lexicologists, fyii ^i\ J as in the 1st Section of the
Muzhir, where it is said that the transmission (JlSi) should be " from such as l^WI V&gt; JI, like [the descendants of] Kahtan
and Ma'add and 'Admin; not from those after them; after the corruption of their language, and the varying of the
Muwelleds." El-Jowharee, as will presently be seen, applies the appellation a^Uii v&gt; 0l even to desert-Arabs of his own time ;
but in doing so, he deviates from the general usage of the lexicologists. As is said in the 6th Section of the Muzhir, the
transmitter must be a trustworthy person ; but may be a woman, and may be a slave, as we have before stated. The degrees
of credit to which the phrases and words thus transmitted are entitled arc distinguished by ranging them in the following
classes: 1st, (as is stated in the 3rd Section of the Muzhir,) the term ^ is applied to that which has been transmitted by
such a number of persons as cannot be supposed to have agreed to a falsehood: 2ndly, Jul (plural of ±J), to what have been
transmitted by some of the lexicologists, but are wanting in that which is required to justify the application, thereto, of the
former term; and what is thus transmitted is also termed ^&amp;.: 3rdly, (as is said in the 5th Section,) #f (plural of £), to
what have been transmitted by only one of the lexicologists; and what is thus transmitted, if the transmitter is a person of
exactness, as Aboo-Zcyd and El-Khaleel and others, is admitted: 4thly, (as is said in the 15th Section,) ' M £&gt; (plural of
^yu), to words known to be spoken only by one Arab. It was only when all other sources failed to supply what was wanted,
that recourse was had, by the writers of lexicons and lexicological works, to contemporary Arabs of the desert ; and I do not
find that much reliance was often placed upon these after the end of the third century of the Flight El-Jowharee, who died
near the close of the next century, states, in the short preface to his "Sihah," that what he had collected in El-'Irak for his
lexicon he "rehearsed by Up to [those whom he terms] a^UJl v &gt; in their abodes in the desert (aJ&gt;00 :" but this he seems to
have done rather to satisfy any doubts that he may have'had, and to obtain illustrations, than with the view of taking such
persons as authorities for words or phrases or significations. It is related of Aboo-Zeyd, in the 7th Section of the Muzhir, that
he said, "I do not say 'the Arabs say' unless I have heard it from these: Bckr Ibn-Hawazin and Bcnoo-Kilab and Benoo-
Hihil ; or from [the people of] the higher portion of the lower region, or [of] the lower of the higher :"* and that Yoonus used
the expression "the Trustworthy (i&amp;i) told me from the Arabs;" that being asked, "Who is the Trustworthy V he answered,
"Aboo-Zcyd;" and being asked, "And wherefore dost thou not name him?" he answered, "He is a tribe, so I do not
name him."t

Most of the contents of the best Arabic lexicons was committed to writing, or to the memories of students, in the latter
half of the second century of the Flight, or in the former half of the next century. Among the most celebrated lexicological



first of these from the Mo'allaknh of Imra-cWKeys. It would have been
strange, indeed, if this had not l»ecn the case : for, except the l£ur-an,
nothing was so highly prized by the lexicologists as the pagan poetry :
every fragment of it was most valuable in their estimation, and most
carefully sought after and preserved ; and the intentional corruption of it
they regarded as almost a crime.

• "Aboo-'Amr said, 'The most chaste in speech, of men, are the
higher [in respect of territory] of [the tribe of] Temeem, and the lower of
[the tribe of] £eys :' nnd Aboo-Zeyd said, ' The most chaste in speech, of
men, arc [the people of] the lower portion of the higher region, and the
higher of the lower,' meaning the rear of [the tribe of] Hawazin ; the
people of the higher region being the people of El-Medeeneh, and those
around it, and those next it, and those near it, whose dialect he held to be
not the same as that [of Hawazin]." (Muzhir, 49th Section.) According
to the £amoos, the higher region (ii»WI) is " what is above Nejd, to the



land of Tihimeh, to the part behind Mekkeh; and certain town., or
villages outside El-Medecneh."

t The exclusion of post-classical words and significations in the best
Arabic lexicons, or their specification as such when they occur therein, is
of very great importance to us in the use that wc are often obliged to
make of those lexicons in interpreting the Hebrew Scriptures. Thus the
triumph of El-Islam, by occasioning the corruption of the Arabic language
and the composition of such lexicons, has rendered us a most signal
service. I have seldom noticed correspondences between the Arabic on
the one side and the Hebrew and other Semitic languages on the other,
because, though these are often illustrated by means of the incomparable
copiousness of the Arabic, the Arabic is rarely illustrated by them, and
because we have no such authorities for the interpretation of those
languages as we have for the interpretation of the Arabic.



xii



PREFACE.



works, general and special, of this period, are the " 'Eyn," commonly ascribed to El-Khalcel, who died in the year of the Flight
160 or 170 or 175 (aged 74); the "Nawadir" of El-Kisa-ce, who died in 182 or 183 or 189 or 192; tho " Jeem" and the
"Nawadir" and the work entitled " El-Ghareeb el-Musannaf" of Aboo-'Amr Esh-Sheybance, who died in 205 or 206 or 213
(aged 110 or 111 or 118); the "Nawadir" and the " Logluit" of El-Farra, who died in 207 (aged 67); the "Loghaf of
Aboo-'Obeydeh, who died 1n 208 or 209 or 210 or 211 (aged 96 or 97 or 98 or 99); the "Nawadir" and the "Loghat"
of Aboo-Zeyd, who died in 214 or 215 or 216 (aged 93); the "Ajnas" of El-Asma'ee, who died in 215 or 216 (aged 92 or
93) ; the work entitled "El-Ghareeb el-Musannaf" of Aboo-'Obeyd, who died in 223 or 224 or 230 (aged 67); and the
".Nawadir" of. Ibn-El-Aardbee, who died in 231 or 233 (aged 81 or 83): all mentioned near the close of the 1st Section of
the Muzhir. From these and similar works, either immediately or through the medium of others in which they arc cited, and
from oral tradition, and, as long as it could be done with confidence, by collecting information from Arabs of the desert, were
composed all the best lexicons, and commentaries on the classical poets &amp;c. The most authoritative of such works are the
lexicons; and the most authoritative of these are, of course, generally speaking, the later, because every succeeding
loxicographcr profited by the critical research of his predecessors, and thus avoided or corrected errors committed by earlier
authors. The commentaries on the poets and on the Traditions have contributed largely to the lexicons. They often present
explanations that have been disallowed or questioned by eminent lexicographers; and therefore their statements, when uncon-
firmed by other authorities, must be received with caution : but in many cases their explanations are unquestionably accurate,
and they afford valuable aid by giving examples of words and phrases of doubtful meanings. The danger of relying upon a
single early authority, however high that authority may be, in any matter of Arabic lexicology, will be shown by innumerable
instances in the present work. I here speak of errors of judgment. In addition to these, we have mistranscription*. A
word once mistranscribed is repeated in copy after copy ; and at length, from its having been found in several copies, is
confidently regarded as correct.* The value of the larger and later and more esteemed lexicons cannot, therefore, be too
highly rated.

The first of the general lexicons is that which is commonly ascribed to El-Khalccl, entitled the "'Eyn" (J^i\ v d£&gt;) ;
and this has served in a great measure as the basis of many others. In it the words are mentioned according to their
radical letters, as in all the best lexicons; but the letters are arranged, with the exception of I and ^, which arc classed with ^
for obvious reasons, nearly in the order of their places of utterance, as follows ; commencing with * (whence the title) :

Under each of these letters, in the foregoing order, except the last three which arc necessarily chissed together, arc mentioned
all the words of which the roots contain that letter without any letter of those preceding it in this arrangement : first, tho
bilitcral-radical words : then, the trilitcral-radical ; of which arc placed first the sound ; secondly the unsound in one letter ;
and thirdly the unsound in two letters : next, the quadrilitcral-radical : and lastly, the quinquelitcral-radioal. Thus, under
the letter ^ are mentioned all the words of which the roots contain that letter: under -., all the words of which the roots contain
that letter without ^: under ., all of which the roots contain that letter without c or -. : and so on. For instance, in the
section of the letter J, we find, in the first division, first, ^j ; then, oU and jj ; and so on: and in the second division, first, ju



* For instance, M. Frcsncl quoted (in the second of his " Lcttrcs
sur l'Histoire des.Arabcsavant l'lslamisme," in the "Journal Asiatique,"
3rd Series, vol. iii. pp. 330 ct scq.,) an extract from the " Kitiib cl-
Aghdncc," as containing, in the phrases ^jj U-n' ^t Ij^lj c-JU »- U
W *3^» two words supposed by him, and by his and my learned friend
the sheykh Mohammad 'Eiyad E{-Tan{awcc, (see pp. 324 ct seq. of that
letter,) to be wanting in all the Arabic dictionaries. One of these words
is written U*u, as alwve, in one of M. Frcsncl's copies of the " Kitab el-
Aghancc," three in number; in another copy, '« v&gt;~ ; and in the third
copy, U-iJ: the other is in all the- copies UJ, as above: and they are



explained in that work, on the authority of Abu-1-Yakdhan El-Joafee
as meaning ^^uaJt J-^.3 &gt;vtJ' y.i \j mid *-jj J-» »^»j *-jU sj\.
The former word is correctly U^l* or lauaJ, both infinitive nouns of
oouij. Ihc other word is a mistranscription for lw. My lamented
friend M. Fresnel was always glad to receive and admit a correction of
any of his own rare mistakes; and in his " Fourth Letter" he announced
that the sheykh Mohammad had afterwards rectified these two errors.















PREFACE.



xm



and j&gt;b ; then, ^j and jj ; and so on : all the combinations of the same radical letters being arranged consecutively; and
the same order of letters being observed in all cases. Respecting the question of its authorship, which is involved in
much uncertainty, I have gathered from the 1st Section of the Muzhir what here follows. Es-Scerafee says that El-
Khalecl composed the first part of the 'Eyn. But most men deny [absolutely] its being his composition. Some say
that it is by Lcyth [or El-Lcyth] Ibn-Nasr Ibn-Seiyar El-Khurasanoe. El-Azhercc says tbat El-Leyth composed it, and
ascribed it to El-Khalccl in order that it might bocome in much request. Some say that El-Khalecl composed the
portion from the beginning to the end of the letter e, and El-Leyth completed it ; and therefore it is that the first part
docs not resemble the rest. Ibn-El-Moatezz relates, on the authority of the " Moajam el-TJdaba " of Yitkoot El-
Hamawce, that El-Khalecl made himself solely and peculiarly an associate of El-Leyth ; and when he composed the
'Eyn, assigned it to him : that El-Lcyth held it in very great estimation, and gave him a hundred thousand [dirhems] ;
and committed the half of it to memory :* but it happened that he purchased a highly-prized female slave, who, be-
coming jealous of the daughter of his paternal uncle [i. c. of his wife], and desiring to enrage him, which sho could not
do with respect to money as he would not care for her doing this, burned that book : and as no one else possessed a copy
of it, and El-Khalccl had then died, El-Lcyth dictated the half that he retained in his memory, and employed persons
to complete it uniformly with that half: and they made this composition which is in the hands of men. To account for
the mistakes occurring in the 'Eyn, Thaalab says, " El-Khaleel sketched it out, but did not fill it up ; and had he filled
it up, he had spared nothing in it ; for El-Khalccl was a man of whom tho like has not been seen : certain learned men
filled it up, 011 whose authority nothing has been related." It is also said that El-Khalecl composed, of this book, only
the section of the letter c, and his companion El-Leyth composed the rest, and named himself " El-Khalecl " [i. c. " tho
friend "] ; and that when he says, in the book, " El-Khalecl Ibn- Ahmad says," it is El-Khaleel ; and when he says,
absolutely, " El-Khalccl says," he speaks of himself : and that every flaw in tho book is from him ; not from El-Khaleel.
En-Nawawcc says that [according to some of the learned] tho 'Eyn ascribed to El-Khaleel is only what El-Leyth oollcctcd
from El-Khalccl. + The mistakes in the 'Eyn arc numerous ; and there are many interpolations in oopies thereof. Several
authors have applied themselves to point out and correct these faults : some, in works specially devoted to this object :
some, in abridgments of the 'Eyn or in other lexicons. But in general the mistakes are confined to matters of inflec-
tion and derivation ; not extending to tho insertion of false or unknown words : and such mistakes arc of light account. J

The following notices of other celebrated lexicons, composed after the 'Eyn, so far as to include tho
Kamoos, I borrow chiefly from the same section of the Muzhir; distinguishing my own additions by enclosing
them within square brackets.

Among the celebrated lexicons composed after tho model of the 'Eyn, is the '* Jcmharah " of Ibn-Dureyd,
[who is said to have died in the year of the Flight 321, and to have lived 93 years.] Some say that it is one of tho
best of lexicons ; and it has been taken as an authority by Aboo-'Alee El-Fariseo and Aboo-'Alee Fi-Kalee and Es-
Sccrafec and other eminent authors. Ibn-Jinneo disparages it for faults similar to those of the 'Eyn : and Niftawcyh,
whom Ibn-Dureyd had satirized, pronounced it to be untrustworthy; but without justice.



* Many of the Arabs have been remarkable for a tenacity of memory
almost miraculous. Several of them are related to have composed and
dictated from memory large works, including even lexicons. At school,
they generally lenrn the whole of the Kur-;in by heart, aided to do so by
its being composed in rhyming prose: and many students, among them,
when unable to purchase works necessary to them, borrow such works, a
portion at a time, from the libraries of the mosques, and commit their
entire contents to memory. Hence, in numerous instances, the variations
in copies of the same Arabic work ; copies being often written from the
dictation of persons who have learned a work by heart.

t lin-Nawawee also says, (see the printed edition of his Biographical
fck. r.



Dictionary, page 231,) that, according to some of the learned, "much of
what El-Azheree has transcribed in the Tahdheeb el-Loghah from the
Eyn is of the mistakes of Lcyth :" but this is inconsistent with the
estimation in which the Tahdheeb is held by lexicographers of the highest
repute. El-Azheree often points out what he terms mistakes of El-
Leyth, and corrects them',

J In the present work, whatever is given as on the authority of El-
Leyth is from the 'Eyn ; I believe, through the medium of the Tahdheeb
of El-Azheree, except, perhaps, in a very few instances : and from the
'Eyn also is generally derived (probably in almost every instance) what
is given as on the authority of El-KhaleeL



» T PREFACE.



The " Tahdheeb " of El-Azheree, [who was born in the year of the Plight 282, and died in the year 370 or 371.
This is a very excellent lexicon, and one from which I have largely drawn, immediately and through the medium of
the Lisan el-' Arab and of the Taj-el-' Aroos. Its arrangement is the same as that of the 'Eyn, which it calls " the book
of El-Leyth," and from which its contents are in a great measure derived. I possess a large portion of this work in a
volume of the "Tahdheeb et-Tahdheeb ;" and a small portion, consisting of 193 pages, of a copy in large 8vo., cor-
responding to a part of the former.]

The " Mohcet " of the Sahib Ibn-'Abbad. [Ibn-Khillikan* states that he was born in the year of the Flight
326, and died in 385: and describes this work as "in seven volumes; arranged in the order of the letters of tho
alphabet; copious in words, but having few confirmatory examples :" thus resembling the Kiimoos. Much has been
drawn from it in my own lexicon.]

Tho " Mujmal " of Ibn-Faris, [who died in the year of the Flight 390 or 395.] He restricted himself, in his
lexicon, to tho mention of genuine words ; excluding the unfamiliar and ignored ; on the authority of oral tradition,
and from books of good repute; aiming, as he says, at abridgment and conciseness. [His work is highly esteemed.
Tho arrangement is that of the usual order of the letters of the alphabet.]

The " Sihah," or, as some call it, " Sahah," of El- Jowharee, [commonly, now, pronounced " El-Joharce," who
died, according to Abu-1-Fida, in tho year of the Flight 398, and " was from Firab, a city of the country of the Turks,
beyond tho river," that is, beyond the Seyhoon : or, according to Ibn-Esh-Shihnch, he died in the year 397, as I,find
in two copies of his history in my possession : or, according to Hajjec Khalccfeh, in 393.] Et-Tcbrcczec says that it is
commonly known by the title of the ^Lf, which is pi. of ^J, , but that some call it the ^.LLZ, which is synonymous
with ^Ja. As its title imports, the author restricted himself to the mention of genuine words, like Ibn-Faris, his
contemporary. [But his lexicon is far more comprehensive, and more excellent in every respect, than that of Ibn-
Faris.] As he says in his preface, he composed it in an order which none had before pursued, [mentioning each word
according to the place of the last letter of the root, and then the first and second, in the usual order of the alphabet,]
after collecting the contents in El-'Irak, and rehearsing them by lip [as I have before mentioned] to [those whom he
torms] a^wi ^\ in their abodes in the desert (a^ui). Eth-Tha'alibee says that ho was one of the wonders of the ago.
His lexicon, however, is not free from instances of inadvertence or mistakes, like all great books ; and such as cannot
bo attributed to the copyists. Yakoot says, in the " Moajam el-Udaba,» that the cause of the mistranscriptions in it
was this : when he had composed it, it was read to him as far as [the section of] the letter ,&gt;, and an evil suggestion
occurred to his mind, in consequence of which he cast himself from a housetop, and died : so the rest of the book
remained a rough draught, not pruned, or trimmed, nor fairly copied out ; and his disciple Ibrahecm Ibn-Salih El-
Warrak made a fair copy of it, and committed mistakes in some places in it. Ibn-Barrcc wrote a commentary, or
series of annotations, (^£* plural of a^u.,) on the Sihah, [an extremely valuable work] in which ho reached tho
middle [of the section] of the letter ^ ; and the sheykh 'Abd- Allah Ibn-Mohammad El-Bustec completed it. [But I
have invariably found passages from every part of it cited as the sayings of Ibn-Barree.] And Es-Saghanec, or, as
he is called by some, Es-S&amp;ghanee, wrote a Tekmileh (&amp;JS, i. e. Supplement) to the Sihah ; exceeding it in bulk. [Some
further remarks on the Sihah (my own copies of which have been already described) will be found in my account of tho
Kamoos. The abridgment entitled " Mukhtar es-Sihah " is well known : it is too scanty to be of much use except to
those who desire to commit to memory the most usual words and significations. A very superior abridgment is tho
" Jami' " of the seyyid Mohammad Ibn-es-seyyid-Hasan, which was finished, according to Hajjee Khalecfeh, in the
year of the Flight 854. It is copious, well digested, and enriched with additions from the Mughrib of El-Mutarrizee,
the Fa'ik of Ez-Zamakhsheree, the Nihayeh of Ibn-El-Atheer, &amp;c. Of this work I possess a very good copy.]



• I have the express authority of the Taj el-' Aroos (in art. iUU.) for thus writing the name of this author.



PREFACE. xt

The "Jami"' of El-Kazzaz, [who died in the year of the Flight 412. Hajjee Khaleefeh mentions it as "an esteemed
oook, but rare." It is not unfrequently c : ted in the Taj el-'Aroos.]

The "Moo'ab" (thus, with fet-h to the c,) of Aboo-Ghalib Ibn-Teniam, [or, according to Ibn-Khillikan, Aboo-Ghdlib
Temdm,] known by the appellation of Ibn-Et-Teiyanee, [who died in the year of the Flight 436 ;] a work of very great utility,
consisting of what is correct of the contents of the 'Eyn, not omitting anything of the confirmatory examples from the Kur-an
and the Traditions and the genuine poems of the Arabs, but rejecting what it contains of examples respecting which there is
disagreement, and of mistranscribed words, and faulty formations ; and adding what Ibn-Dureyd lias added in the Jcmharah.
It is rarely found; for people have not persevered in transcribing it, but have rather inclined to the Jcmharah of Ibn-Dureyd
and the Mohkam of Ibn-Sccdch and the Jami' of El-Kazzaz and the Sihah &amp;c.

The " Mohkam" of Ibn-Seedeh the Andalusian, who was blind, [as was also his father; and who died in the year of the
Flight 458, aged about GO years.] This is the greatest of the lexicological books [i. e. of the lexicons] composed since the age
of the Siliiih [to the time of the author of the Muzhir, of those known to him. It follows the arrangement of the 'Eyn; and
it is held in very high estimation for its copiousness, its accuracy, its critical remarks, and its numerous examples from
classical poets. In copiousness and in some other respects, it is superior, and in others hardly (if at all) inferior, to the Sihah.
It is one of the two chief sources of the Kainoos; the other being the 'Obab of Es-Sagluincc : and I have drawn from it very
largely, both immediately and through the medium of the Lisan el-'Arab and of the Taj cl-'Aroos, for my own lexicon. I
I&gt;ossess the last fifth part of it in a volume of the "Tahdheeb et-Tahdhecb ;" and another large portion, and a smaller portion,
of a most admirable copy which has been dispersed, written in the year of the Flight G75, for the library of a Sultan,
apparently the celebrated Beybars.]

[The " Asiis " of Ez-Zamakhshcrce, who was born in the year of the Flight 4G7, and died in 538. This lexicon is a
very excellent repertory of choice and chaste words and phrases ; and especially and peculiarly valuable as comprising a very
large collection of tropical significations, distinguished as such, which has greatly contributed, by indirectly illustrating proper
significations as well as otherwise, to the value of my own lexicon, as my numerous citations of it will show, although I have
generally been obliged to draw from it through the medium of the Taj cl-'Aroos, which often does not name it in quoting it.
Its order is the same as that of the Mujmal, apparently in most copies : but some, which arc said to be abridged, follow the
order of the Sihah. 1

• • • J

[The "Mughrib" of El-Mutarrizec, who was born in Khuwarczm, in the year of the Flight 53G, and died in G10.
This is a lexicon of select words and. phrases, and particularly of such as occur in books of Traditions, and other works relating
to the law. It forms a very valuable companion and supplement to the other lexicons; and I have constantly consulted it and
drawn from it in composing the present work. Its arrangement of the roots is that of the usual order of the alphabet, with
respect to the first, second, and third letters of each. I possess a very excellent copy of it, written in the year of the Flight
977, presented to me by the Rev. J. R. T. Licdcr, late of the English Church-Mission in Cairo.]

The " 'Obab" of Es-Saghancc, or Es-Sagh&amp;nee, [who was born in the year of the Flight 577, and died in GGO, according to
the Muzhir (48th Section), or, as is said in the Taj el-'Aroos (art. o*-0&gt; in ^ 5 » on tlie authority of one who attended his funeral.]
This, after the Mohkam, is the greatest of the lexicological works composed since the age of the Sihah [to the time of the
author of the Muzhir, of those known to him. It was left unfinished. If, as I believe is the case, it follow the order of
the Sihah, the portion completed was somewhat more than three fourths; for] the author reached, in it, to the section of^c,:
which occasioned the saying,






xn PREFACE.

[" Verily Es-Saghdnee, who mastered the sciences and the doctrines of philosophy, the utmost of his case was that he reached
to jjif" which signifies " dumbness," &amp;c. — Though a man of extensive learning, he was opiniative, and addicted to unjust
criticism of his superiors. A copy of the 'Obdb, and a copy of the same author's Supplement to the Sihah, before mentioned,
used by the author of the Taj cl-'Aroos, belonged to the library of the mosque of the Emecr Sarghatmish, in Cairo ; but on my
causing an inquiry to be made for them, the librarian declared that they were no longer found there. They have probably
been stolen ; or had not been returned by the author of the Taj el-'Aroos when he died ; on which occasion, it is said, his house
was plundered of the books &amp;c. that he left.]

[The "Lisdn el-' Arab" of Ibn-Mukarram, who was born in the year of the Flight 630, and died in 711. In the copy
of his lexicon in the library of the collegiate mosque called the " Ashrafecych," in Cairo, consisting of twenty-eight quarto-
volumes, he is styled " Jcmdl-ed-Dcen Mohammad Ibn-csh-sheykh-el-imam-cl-marhoom-JcIdl-cd-Decn-Abi-l-'Izz-Mukarrain Ibn-
esh-sheykh-Ncjecb-cd-Dcen-Abi-1-Hasan-El-Ansiirce:" but in tlie Tsij cl-'Aroos, lie is almost always called Ibn-Mandhoor
( mAIi ^t). I shall give an account of this great work in describing the Taj cl-'Aroos.]

[The " Tahdhccb ct-Tahdhceb" of Mahmood Et-Tanoolchw, who died in the year of the Flight 723. It is a combination
of the contents of the Mohkain and Tahdhccb (the former occupying the (ir^t place in each article) with a few additions from other
sources. Thus it forms one of the best and most comprehensive of the Arabic lexicons, without any exceptions known to me but
the Lisiin el-'Arab and the Taj cl-'Aroos. Of the original autograph copy of this work, in five full-paged, large quarto-volumes,
I possess the last volume, consisting of 501 pages. I made a diligent search for the other volumes, but, without success.]

[The "Misb;uY;of El-Feiyoomcc (Ahmad Jim- Mohammad Ibn-'Alec El-Mukri). Its full title is " Kl-Misbah cl-Munccr
fee Chareeb csh-Sharh cl-Kebcer." This is a lexicon similar to the Mughrib, above mentioned; but. much more comprehensive;
forming a most valuable companion and supplement to the larger lexicons. Notwithstanding its title, it comprises a very large
collection of classical words and phrases and significations of frequent occurrence ; in many instances with more clear and full
explanations than I have found elsewhere. I have therefore constantly drawn from it in composing my own lexicon ; possessing
a very accurate copy of it, a full-paged quarto-volume of 742 pages. Its author states in it that he finished its composition in
the year of the Flight 734.]

[The " Mughnec," as it is commonly called, or " Mughni-1-Lcbccb," of the celebrated grammarian Ilm-IIishsim, who was
born in the year of the Flight 708, and died in 761 or the following year. A large work, whereof a little more than one half
consists of an elaborate lexicon of the particles and similar words, for which it is my chief authority, as it was, also, that of the
author of the Kiimoos, whose explanations of the particles arc, however, very meagre and unsatisfactory. I am fortunate in
possessing a most excellent copy of it, a quarto-volume of GOO pages.]

The " Kdmoos " of El-Fcyroozabadee, [or, as some pronounce it, EI-Fccroozdbddce, (from the city of FcnSzdbdd, or
Feerdzdbdd, pronounced by the Arabs Fcyroozdbad, or Fecroozdbdd,) who was born in the year of the Flight 729, and died in
816.*] This, after the Mohkam and the 'Obab, is the greatest of the lexicological works composed since the age of the Sihdh
[to the time of the author of the Muzhir, of those known to him] : but none of these three [ho adds] has attained to be as
much used as the Sihtlh ; nor has the rank of the Sihdh, nor its celebrity, been diminished by the existence of these ; because
it is restricted to what is genuine, so that it is, among the books of lexicology, like the Saheeh of El-Bukhdrcc among the books



* It is stated at the end of article j*-) in the T;ij cl-'Aroos that the
author of the Kiimoos wrote at the end of the first .volume of the second
copy of that work made by his own hand, which volume ended with the



article above mentioned, that he finished the transcription of (hat volume
in Dhu-l-Itijjeh 7G8.






TREFACE. xvn



of traditions ; for the point upon which turns the title to reliance is not the copiousness of the' collection, but the condition of
genuineness, or correctness. [The judgment thus expressed, as to the rank and celebrity of the Sihah, in comparison with the
Kamoos, I have found to agree with the opinion of the most learned men among the Arabs with whom I have been acquainted.
But to insinuate that the words and significations added in the latter of these lexicons to those of the former are generally less
genuine, or less correct, is not just : they may be truly said to be generally less chaste, inasmuch as they are less usual : but
their collector has undoubtedly rendered a great service to the students of Arabic by these additions, which have of late years
caused the copies of his lexicon to become much more numerous than those of the Sihah. The value of the Sihah consists in
its presenting a very judicious collection of the most chaste words, with critical illustrations from the best of the lexicologists,
and examples from the best of the classical poets. The Kamoos is little more than what may be termed an enormous
vocabulary ; a collection of words and significations from preceding lexicons and similar works, (for otherwise, according to the
principles of Arabic lexicology as universally taught, they would be of no authority,) mainly from the Mohkam and the 'Obab;
with very few critical observations, many of which arc false,* and scarcely any examples from the poets. Thus it resembles
the Mohcct of Ibn-'Abbad, before mentioned. In order to make room for his numerous additions, desiring that the bulk of his
took should be nearly the same as that of the Sihah, the author has often abridged his explanations in such a manner as to
render them unintelligible to the most learned of the Arabs, and has omitted much of what is most valuable of the contents of
the latter work, But he has frequently deviated from this his usual practice for the purpose of inserting criticisms of others,
without acknowledgment, and apparently some few of his own, upon points in the Sihah in which its author is asserted to have
erred; and this he has often done so as to lead to the belief that the author of the Sihah has affirmed what he has merely
quoted from another. Many of these criticisms I havc^found to have been borrowed from the Annotations on the Sihah by
Ibn-Barrcc and El-Bust.ee, or from the Supplement to the Sihah by Es-Saghance: generally when they arc false, (which is
often the case,) though sometimes when they are correct, from the latter of these works. I have fell it to be my duty to make
thews remarks in defence of El-Jowharce, and for the sake of truth. Abundant proofs of their correctness will be found in my
own lexicon. They may surprise many, who have not known the fact that the Kamoos is very little more than an abridged
compilation from other works: and another fact, to be mentioned in the next paragraph, which will be in a measure
supplementary to this brief account of the Kamoos, will probably surprise them more. — This is the latest of the lexicons
noticed in the Muzhir: therefore I have no further occasion for the use of the square brackets to distinguish my own statements
or opinions from those of the author of that work, which has thus far afforded me so much aid in my account of the
principles of Arabic lexicology, and of the most celebrated Arabic lexicons, as well as in my remarks on the history of the
language. My own, most valuable, manuscript-copy of the Kamoos, which I have already described, has been of very great
use to me, though its text is generally most correctly given in the Taj el-'Aroos. I have also constantly had before me the
edition printed at Calcutta. This is certainly more accurate than most of the manuscript-copies; but it contains countless
false readings, which show that, in many instances, the editor, notwithstanding his unquestionable learning and his possession
of eleven copies, did not understand what he edited. It seems that he must often have given the worst of the readings of his
originals, from neglecting to study the passages in which they occur. I have not thought it necessary to mention all of the
false readings in his edition ; but I have mentioned many of them.]

The "Li'iini'" of El-Fcyroozabadee. Its full title is"El-Liimi' el-Moalara el-'Ojab cl-Jami* beyn el- Mohkam wa-1-
'Obiib." From some words in the preface to the Kamoos, it has been inferred that the author of that work had composed a
lexicon in sixty volumes, bearing the foregoing title, from which, chiefly, he composed, or abridged, the Kamoos, in two
volumes. But in a very learned work, of Annotations on the Kamoos, by Mohammad Ibn-Et-Teiyib El-Fasec, it is clearly



• The judgment and memory of its author are often in fault: for
instance, in article ^/^ he disallows the expression j^a-JI j^i^, and in
art. -— ?} he uses it ; and in article -— 6 he disallows ._~o as syn. with



a

~i&gt;, and in article ~-~6 he authorizes it : and many similar instances
might be mentioned.



XV1I1



PREFACE.



shown that tho words from which this inference has been drawn really signify dt,t the author of the Lami' commenced (not that
he completed) this work, and made it, as far as it extended, to surpass every other work of a similar kind; but that he
imagined it would be, in sixty volumes, too large for students to acquire or read ; and, being requested to compose before it a
conc.se lexicon, he applied himself to the composition of the Kamoos, and abridged the matter of which the Lami' was to have
cons.sted, so a, to comprise the essence of each thirty of the intended volumes in one volume. Thus the words in question are
so far from b.ing a proof of the completion of the Lami', that their literal meaning indicates the very contrary of this. They
arc not, however, the only evidence that we have on this point : for the same eminent scholar to whose Annotations on the
Kamoos I have referred above quotes, from the biographical memoir of the author of the Lami* in the "Tabakat cn-Nohah" of
Es-Suyootcc, the direct assertion that this work was never completed. He also states, as docs likewise" the 'author of the Taj
cl-'Aroos, that more than one writer has transmitted, on the authority of the handwriting of its author, a proof of its non-
completion : for they relate the fact of his having written upon the back of the Lami' that, if he had been able to complete it,
.t wouhl have composed a hundred volumes, [of what size he does not give the least notion,] and that he completed Ave
volumes of it. This, it should be observed, is not inconsistent with what has been said before : it appears that the work would
have consisted of a hundred volumes, each of the size of one of the five volumes that were completed; or would have composed
sixty larger volumes. 13ut I rather incline to think that its author roughly calculated, at one time, that the whole would
consist of a hundred volumes; and at another time, that it would consist of sixty; and that both estimates are greatly beyond
the truth. The non-completion of the Lami' is therefore certain; but this is not so much to be regretted as some persons
might imagine from its author's statement respecting it in his preface to the Kamoos; for the work appears, from its title, to
have been, as far as it extended, with respect to the words ami significations, mainly a compilation uniting the contents of the
Mohkam and the 'Obab, and neither of these lexicons has been lost to the world. From a reference to it in article &lt;* of the
Kamoos, (in which the author asserts his having disproved an opinion respecting the signification of ^ without stating
that El-Azherec had done so more than five centuries before,) it seems that the Lami' (seeing how small a portion of k
was completed) followed the order of the 'Eyn and the Mohkam ; for article &lt;S is in tho third of the main divisions of these
two works, but in the last but two of those of the Kamoos. Considering this fact, and that the main divisions of the 'Eyn and
the Mohkam necessarily decrease in length from first to last, I suppose that the author of the five volumes of the Lami' wrote
them, agreeably with a common practice, with large margins for additions, and calculated that, with these additions, each of
the five volumes would form at least three.

The "Taj cl-'Aroos," the enormous extent of which I have mentioned in the second paragraph of this preface, is said to.
have been commenced, in Cairo, soon after the middle of the last century of our era, by the scyyid Murtada Ez-Zcbccdec. At
the end of a copy of it in his own handwriting, he states that it occupied him fourteen years and some days. According to
the modern historian of Egypt, El-Jabartcc, he was born A.D. 1732 or 1733 : came to Cairo A.D. 1753: finished the Taj
cl-'Aroos A.D. 17G7 or 17G8 : and died A.D. 1791 (in the year of the Flight 1205). And the same historian says that
Mohammad IJcy Abu-dh-Dhahab, for the copy of that work which is in tho library of his mosque, gave him a hundred
thousand dirhems (or drachms) of silver. It is a compilation from tho best and most copious of the preceding Arabic lexicons
and other lexicological works, in the form of an interwoven commentary on the Kamoos; exhibiting fully and" clearly, from the
original sources, innumerable explanations which are so abridged in the latter work as to be unintelligible to the most learned
men of the East; with copious illustrations of the meanings &amp;c, corrections of mistakes in the Kamoos and other lexicons, and
examples in prose and verse ; and a very lanrc collection of additional words and significations, mentioned under the roots
to which they belong. Of the works from which it is compiled, though I believe that it was mainly derived in the first
instance from the Lisan el-' Arab, more than a hundred arc enumerated by the seyyid Murtada in his preface. Among these
arc— 1. The " Sihah," a copy in eight volumes, in the handwriting of Yakoot Er-lloomcc, with useful marginal notes
determining the corrcat readings &amp;c. by Ibn-Barree [and El-Bustec] and Aboo-Zekcrceya Et-Tebrcczcc ; in the library [of the
collegiate mosque] of the Emeer Ezbck.— 2. The «• Tahdhceb" of El-Azhcree, a copy in sixteen volumes.— 3. The "Mohkam"






PREFACE. *i*

of Ibn-Seedeh, a copy in eight volumes.— 4. The " Tahdheeb el-Abniyeh wa-l-Af al," by Ibn-El-Kattda, in two volumes.—
5. The " Lisan el-' Arab," by the Imam Jemdl-ed-Deen Mohammad Ibn-'Alee El-Ifreekee, [whose appellations I have more
fully given before, commonly called (in the Taj el-'Aroos) " Ibn-Mandhoor,"] in twenty-eight volumes, the copy transcribed
from the original draught of the author, during his life-time: [of this copy I have often made use in composing my Own
lexicon; and I have found it very helpful, especially in enabling me to supply syllabical signs, which are too often omitted in
the copies of the Taj el-'Aroos :] its author followed closely, in its composition, the Sihdh, the Tahdheeb, the Mohkam, the
Nihdych, the Annotations of Ibn-Barree [and El-Bustce on the Sihdh], and the Jemharah of Ibn-Dureyd: [he also drew from
innumerable other sources, to which he refers in his work.] — 6. The "Tahdheeb et-Tahdheeb" of Abu-th-Thena Mahraood Ibn-
Abce-Bekr Ibn-Hdmid Et-Tanookhce, a copy in five volumes, [of which, as I have already mentioned, I possess the last,] the
original draught of the author, who closely followed, in its composition, the Sihdh, the Tahdheeb, and the Mohkam, with the
utmost accuracy: he died in the year of the Flight 723. — 7. The " Kitdb el-Ghareebeyn" of Aboo-'Obeyd El-Harawee.—
8. The "Nihiiyeh fee Gharecb cl-Hadceth," by Ibn-El-Athccr [Mejd-cd-Dcen] El-Jezeree.— 9. The " Kifdyet el-Mutahaffidh,"
by lbn-El-Ajddbcc, with Expositions thereof.— 10. The " Fascch" of Thaalab, with three Expositions thereof.— 1 1 und 12. The
"Fikh cl-Loghah" and the work entitled " El-Muddf wa-1-Mcnsoob," each by Aboo-Mansoor Eth-Tha'dlibee. — 13 and 14. The
" 'Obiib" and the " Tckmilch fi-fi-Rihdb," each by Er-Radcc Es-Saghdnee, in the library [of the mosque] of the Emeer
Sarghatmish.— 15. The "Misbah" [of El-Fciyoomce].— 1G. The "Takrccb" of Ibn-Khateeb.— 17. The " Mukhtdr es-Sihdh,"
by Er-Rdzco. — 18, 19, nnd 20. The "Asds" and the "Fdlk" and the " Mustakseen-1-Amthdl,'' all three by Ez-Zamakhsheree.—
21. The "Jemharah" of Ibn-Dureyd, in four volumes, in the library [of the mosque] of El-Mr-eiyad.— 22. The " Isldh cl-
Miintik" of Ibn-Es-Sikkect.— 23 and 24. The "Khasdi's" of Ibn-Jinnee, and the "Sirr cs-Sind'ah" of the same author. —
25. The " MujnuU" of Ibn-Fdris. — Many other works of great value arc included in the same list. And the Annotations on
the Kamoos by his preceptor, Mohammad Ibn-Et-Tciyib El-Fascc, (before mentioned, in my account of the Lami',) must be
especially noticed as a very comprehensive and most learned work, from which the seyyid Murtada derived much valuable
matter to incorporate in the Taj el-'Aroos. From these Annotations of 'Mohammad El-Fusee, which have often served to
explain to me obscure passages in the Taj el-'Aroos, and from several others of the most celebrated of the works used by the
scyyid Murtada, I have drawn much matter which he omitted as not necessary to Eastern scholars, but which will be found to
1)C highly important to the Arabic students of Europe. He made very little use of a commentary on the Kamoos entitled the
" Namoos," by Mulla 'Alec cl-Kdri, as it is not a work held in high estimation, and he was most careful to include among his
authorities none but works of high repute. It must also be mentioned that he has bestowed great pains upon the important
task of settling the true text of the Kamoos, according to the authorities of several celebrated copies; and that he has inserted
the various readings that he regarded as being worthy of notice. And here I may state that most of the illustrations of the
text of the Kamoos that arc incorporated in the Turkish translation of that work, whenever I have examined them, which has
often been the case, I have found to be taken from the Taj el-'Aroos, of which the Translator ('Asim Efcndee) is said to have
had a copy in the author's handwriting : but generally speaking, what is most precious of the contents of the latter work has
been omitted in that translation.

As the Taj el-'Aroos is the medium through which I have drawn most of the contents of my lexicon, I must more fully
state the grounds upon which I determined to make so great a use of it Not long after I had become acquainted with this
enormous work, I found it to be asserted by some persons in Cairo that the seyyid Murtada was not its author: that it was
compiled by a certain learned man (whose name I could not ascertain) who, coming to Cairo with this work, on his way from
Western Africa to Mekkch as a pilgrim, and fearing to lose it in the desert-journey, committed it to the seyyid Murtada to be
safely kept until his return: that he died during his on ward -journey, or during his return towards Cairo: and that the seyyid
Murtada published it as his own composition. This grave accusation brought against the reputed author of the Taj el-'Aroos,
unsupported by the knowledge of the name of the person whom he is thus asserted to have wronged, I did not find to be
credited by any of the learned, nor do I myself believe it : but it imposed upon me the necessity of proving or disproving,



XX



PREFACE.



not the genuineness of the book (a matter of no importance except as affecting the reputation of the seyyid Murtada*), but,
its authenticity. I was therefore obliged to make a most laborious collation of passages quoted in it with the same passages in
the works quoted: and in every instance I found that they had been faithfully transcribed. Thus the authenticity of the
Taj el-'Aroos was most satisfactorily established. But in comparing large portions of it with the corresponding portions of the
Lisan el-'Arab, I made the unexpected discovery that, in most of the articles in the former, from three-fourths to about nine-
tenths of the additions to the text of the Kamoos, and in many articles the whole of those additions, existed verbatim in the
Lisan el-'Arab. I cannot, therefore, acquit the seyyid Murtada of a want of candour, and of failing to render due honour to
one of the most laborious of compilers, by not stating either that the Taj el-'Aroos was mainly derived in the first instance
from the Lisan el-'Arab (which I believe to have been the case) or that the contents of the former are mainly found in the
latter. This circumstance has induced me very often to compose articles of my lexicon principally from the Lisan el-'Arab in
preference to the Taj el-'Aroos, comparing the contents afterwards with the latter ; and when they agreed, giving the latter as
my authority in most instances (though not alwaysf) because I could only undertake to have the latter transcribed. The only
copy of the Lisan el-'Arab known to me is that which I have already mentioned. It was lent to me, in successive portions,
from the library of the collegiate mosque called "the Ashrafeeyeh," in Cairo. It is written in several different hands, nearly
resembling one another, of a peculiar cursive kind, which none can correctly read without studying sufficiently to understand
thoroughly; for which reason, if I had been able to obtain any copy made from it (for it bears statements of its having been
several times partially or wholly transcribed some centuries ago) I could not have placed much reliance upon it. Since the
time of the seyyid Murtada, it has suffered much injury, chiefly from the rotting of the paper ; in many places, the whole of
the written portion of a page having fallen out, the margin only remaining.

Having fully satisfied myself of the authenticity of the Taj el-'Aroos, as well as of its intrinsic value, my next object was
to cause a careful transcription of it to be commenced without delay, although, while I remained in Cairo, I made use of copies
belonging to the libraries of mosques. The following are all the copies of that work, or of portions thereof, respecting which I
have been able to procure any information.— 1. The copy made use of by 'Asim Efendee in writing his Turkish Translation of
the Kamoos. This belonged, according to his own statement, made to me, to Yahya Efendee the Hakeem, who for many
years composed the annual Egyptian Almanac published by order of the Government. He said that it was in the handwriting
of the author, in two very larga volumes ; which, though hardly credible, is not absolutely impossible; for the handwriting of
the seyyid Murtada was small and compact : that the Grand Vezeer who was in Egypt during the contest between our own
forces in that country and the French borrowed it of him, and sent it to Constantinople without his permission: and that he
had caused many inquiries to be made for it there, but never learned any tidings of it.— 2. A copy believed to have been
in fourteen folio-volumes, in the handwriting of the author. Of this, the last volume and the last but two are in the library of
the Riwak of the Syrians in the great mosque El-Azhar. The rest of it seems to have been lost. It may be a portion of a
copy which the author retained for himself. When he died, his family kept his death secret for two days ; after which, the
officers of the Government Treasury plundered his house of much property, among which, perhaps, was this copy; and if so, it
may havo fallen into different hands; one person taking a portion ; and another person, another portion.— 3. A copy sent by
the author as a present to the King of San'a. So I was informed on the authority of a person living in Cairo, who asserted that
he conveyed it for the author, and who must have attained to manhood some years before the author's death. He may perhaps
be mistaken as to the work that he conveyed; but this is not probable.— 4. The copy in the library of the mosque of Mohammad
Bey Abu-dh-Dhahab, before mentioned ; said to be in eight thick, full-paged folio-volumes ;J not in the author's handwriting,



• By various other works, he earned a high reputation for learning ;
and I believe that his ability to compose such a work as the Taj el-'Aroos
was never called in question.

t In the articles of which the last radical letter is &gt;, and in those of
which the last is J, I have generally deviated from my usual plan by



indicating the authority of the Lisan el-'Arab rather than that of the Taj
el-'Aroos in order to convey some notion of the value of the former work.
J I was informed that the number of its volumes is eight ; but I was
never allowed to see the whole copy, and, in the course of transcription, I
neglected to note where each volume ended.



PREFACE. xxl

but transcribed under his superintendence, and in part, and perhaps entirely, revised by him. This copy wants a portion from
the commencement of the first main division of the lexicon ; i. e., of W . ^ : it also wants some other, smaller, portions. I
shall have to say more respecting it in the next paragraph.-5. A portion in the handwriting of the author, in my possesion ;
from the commencement of W i V V to the words c4-» J, J W. » article %* »PP¥"g more ta the main P° rtl0n ** ,S
wanting in the copy of Mohammad Bey. It is of a small quarto-size, and ends in the middle of a page.-6. A copy in the
library of the late Ibraheem Pasha, transcribed from that of Mohammad Bey, and said to be incorrectly written.— 7. A large
folio-volume, in my possession, before mentioned, consisting of nearly the whole of the first tenth portion; evidently transcribed
from the copy of Mohammad Bey, for it wants what is deficient in iy^\ V V in the latter copy.

The copy transcribed for me, which is in twenty-four thick quarto-volumes, is partly from the portion, in the handwriting
of the author, in the great mosque El-Azhar; but mainly from the copy of Mohammad Bey ; what is wanting in this last,
in Wl ^ t*ing copied from the MS. No. 5 in the foregoing list ; and very nearly the whole of the other (smaller) portions
that are wanting therein being supplied from the principal source, namely, the Lisan el-'Arab. It is therefore far superior
to the other known copies, in respect of completeness, except the first and third of the copies mentioned in the next preceding
paragraph if these exist and be still entire. But it will not always serve as a perfect test of the correctness of my own
lexicon, although it has been carefully collated with its originals, as I made use of the copy of Mohammad Bey as long as I
remained in Egypt, and have used the Lisan el- 1 Arab and other lexicons for the supplying of syllabical signs &amp;c. wanting
in that copy and in my own. In my copy, diacritical points have often been omitted when not thought by the transcriber to
be absolutely necessary; as is the case in almost all copies of lexicons: also syllabical signs that are in the originals are not
unfrequently omitted: and my copy is more irregular than its originals in the manner of writing the letter hemzeh. The
copy of Mohammad Bey will probably, in a few years, be in many places illegible ; for the ink with which it is written is of
a corrosive nature, and has already, in those parts, eaten through the paper, though hitherto not to such an extent as to present
any difficulty to the reader : or rather 1 should say that such was the case just before my own copy was made ; for while
I was translating from portions of it already transcribed for me, small pieces often dropped out from its leaves, in spite of my
utmost care, Itelieve that if I had not undertaken the composition of the present work, the means of composing such a work
would not much longer have existed. For not only was the sole copy of the Taj el-' Aroos that was nearly complete, and that wet
worthy of reliance, of those known to exist, rapidly decaying; but many of the most precious of the manuscripts from which
it was compiled have been mutilated; many are scattered, no one knows whither; and several, of which no other copies are
known to be in existence, and for which one would have to search from city to city, exploring the libraries of mosques, are
said to have perished. The transcription of my own copy, and its collation, extended over a period of more than thirteen
years. It might have been accomplished in much less time, had less care been bestowed upon it: but for several years I could
find no competent and willing transcriber except the sheykh Ibraheem Ed-Dasookee, who was unable to devote the whole of his
time to this object. Upon him the task of transcription mainly devolved; and the collation was performed wholly by him in
conjunction with myself or with another sheykh.

As soon as a few pages of my copy of the Taj el-' Aroos had been transcribed, I commenced the work of translation and
composition from its originals. I did not hesitate to write my lexicon in English rather than in Latin, because the latter
language is not sufficiently perspicuous nor sufficiently copious. For several years I continued to collect all that I required
for a lexicon as complete as it was possible for me to make it. But I then considered that about one third of what I had
compiled consisted of the explanations of words rarely occurring ; many of them, words that no one student was likely ever to
meet with; and not a few, such as are termed «&amp; or &gt;&lt;fi or M f&gt; (before explained, in page xi. of this preface);
these last being words known only as having been spoke.i, each by a single Arab, or as only once occurring in any writing.
I considered also that the undertaking which I had £ us long been prosecuting was one which would require many more
years for its completion ; and that it was incumbent on me to take into account the uncertain duration of my appointed term
Bk. I.



xxu



PREFACE.



of life, and to occupy myself first with what was most important. I therefore finally determined to divide my lexicon into two
Books : the first to contain all the classical words and significations commonly known to the learned among the Arabs : the other,
those that are of rare occurrence and not commonly known. And I have made such subdivisions as will enable the purchaser
of a copy to bind it in the manner that he may deem most convenient : in two volumes, or in four, or in eight; each to consist
of a portion of Book I. with the corresponding portion of Book II.; or so that all the words in Book I. of which the roots
commence with one letter may be immediately followed by the words in Book II. of which the roots commence with the same
letter. The Second Book will be small in comparison with the First, of which the Part to be first published (i to ± inclusive) will
form about one eighth. In order that it may be possible to bind the whole work in two volumes, I have chosen for it a thin paper.

Nearly twenty years have now elapsed since I commenced this work. Had I foreseen that the whole labour of the
composition must fall upon me or the project be abandoned, and had I also foreseen the length of time that it would require
of me, unaided, I should certainly not have had the courage to undertake it. I had hoped that I should have at least one
coadjutor: and I continued to hope for some years that such might be the case; but by no one have I been aided in the least
degree, except, occasionally, in discussions of difficult points, by the sheykh Ibrahcem Ed-l)asookce ; who has written the
results of some of these discussions on the margins of pages of my copy of the Taj el-'Aroos, generally in his own words, but
often in words dictated by me. For seven years, in Cairo, I prosecuted my task on each of the work-days of the week, after
an early breakfast, until within an hour of midnight, with few and short intervals of rest, (often with no interruption but that
of a few minutes at a time for a meal, and half an hour for exercise,) except on rare occasions when I was stopped by illness,
and once when I devoted three days to a last visit to the Pyramids: I seldom allowed myself to receive a visiter except on
Friday, the Sabbath and leisure-day of the Muslims : and more than once I passed a quarter of a year without going out of
my house. But I must not be supposed to claim much credit for the exercise of self-denial with respect to the pleasures of
society ; for during those seven years passed in Cairo, I had my wife and sister and the hitter's two sons residing with me.
Nor w6uld I here make mention of the severe labour which this work has cost me but for the purpose of guarding against the
imputation of my having been wanting in energy or industry. To convey a due idea of the difficulties of my task would be
impossible. While mainly composing from the Taj el-'Aroos, I have often had before me, or by my side, eight or ten other
lexicons, (presenting three different arrangements of the roots, and all of them differing in the order, or rather disorder, of the
words explained,) requiring to be consulted at the same time. And frequently more than a day's study has been necessary to
enable me thoroughly to understand a single passage: for the strict rules of Arabic lexicology demand that every explanation
be given as nearly as possible in the words in which some person of authority has transmitted it; and many explanations
perfectly intelligible when they were first given became less and less so in succeeding ages, and at length quite unintelligible
to the most learned of living Arabs. Even Ibn-Seedeh often confesses, in the Mohkam, his inability to understand an
explanation or some other statement that he has transmitted. Many explanations, moreover, present instances of what is
termed ^Ci; and instances of a worse kind of license, termed ji£&gt;, are not of unfrequent occurrence: by the former term is
meant a deficiency in what an author writes relying upon the understanding of the reader; and by the latter term, a
deficiency in what he writes without relying upon the reader's knowledge. Often, two synonymous words arc used to explain
each other. Numerous cases of this kind occur in the Kamoos: such, for instance, are ILL and j£&gt;, i^C and % ji^t
and ,ifc»1, and ^jfi and ^j- : and in these cases I have not always found the information that I required by referring to
other lexicons. More frequently, in lieu of an explanation, we find merely the word J^, meaning "well known:" and in a
very large proportion of such cases, what was once " well known" has long ceased to be so. Still more frequently, significations
arc only indicated by the context: in many instances, as clearly as they could be expressed by any words of explanation: but
in many other instances, very obscurely. Many words are rendered by others which are not elsewhere explained in the same
lexicon; many, by words meant to be understood in senses not elsewhere explained in that lexicon; many, by words meant to
be understood in tropical senses; and many, by words meant to be understood in post-classical senses. In these last cases, I
have often found in my knowledge of modern Arabic a solution of a difficulty : but without great caution, such knowledge would






PREFACE. xxiii

frequently have misled me, in consequence of the changes which have taken place in the applications of many words
since the classical age. Great caution is likewise requisite in the attempt to elicit the significations of words by means of
analogy ; as I could easily show by giving all the principal words of one article with their significations, and then requiring
any student to divine the significations of the other words of the same article by such means, and comparing his explanations
with those that have been authoritatively transmitted. Perfect reliance is not to be placed upon vowel-signs and the like when
they are merely written, without their being either described in words or shown by the statement that the word of which the
pronunciation is to be fixed is similar to some other word well known. Even when they are described, one has to consider
what rule the author follows ; and in some lexicons the rules followed by the authors are not explained. For instance, when
a noun of three letters is said to be with fet-h, if in the Eamoos, tne meaning is that it is of the measure Jii : but in some
other lexicons it means that it is of the measure Jii. If we find such a noun in the Ramoos written as of the measure jii and
said to be Avith fet-h, we must infer that jZS (not jii) is the correct measure : and if in the same lexicon we find such a noun
that is to be explained written otherwise than as of the measure Jai, without its being followed by any indication of its
measure, we must infer that J*i is probably its true measure, unless it be a word commonly known. But these and other
technical difficulties arc comparatively small, or become so after a little time spent in the study of different lexicons with a
previous knowledge of the principles of Arabic lexicology and lexicography. Among the graver difficulties arc those which arc
often presented by verses cited as confirmatory examples, or as illustrations, without either context or explanation ; many of
which I have inserted in my lexicon as being either absolutely necessary or such as I could not omit with entire satisfaction.
Various other obstacles that I have had to encounter I refrain from mentioning, hoping that I shall be deemed to have said
enough to excuse myself for the length of timo that has elapsed since the commencement of my work. I have, however,
been unusually favoured by circumstances; and especially by my having acquired, in familiar intercourse with Arabs, an
acquaintance with their manners and customs, and their mental idiosyncrasies, indispensably requisite to success in my
undertaking. Encouraged by these circumstances, I applied myself to the working of the rich mine that I had discovered,
with the resolution expressed in the saying of a poet,*

When I had prosecuted my task in Cairo during a period of nearly six years, I understood it to be the desire of my
Patron that the British Government might be induced to recognise the importance of my work by contributing to the expense
of its composition. I therefore submitted to the Head of Her Majesty's Government a request that my undertaking mi"ht
be thus honoured and promoted : and I did so in a time peculiarly auspicious ; the Premier being Lord John Russell, now
Earl Russell. His Lordship graciously and promptly replied to my appeal by granting me an annual allowance from the Fund
for Special Service; and through his recommendation, this was continued to me by one of his successors in office, another
Nobleman who added eminence in letters to elevation of birth and station, the late Earl of Aberdeen. And here I must
especially and gratefully acknowledge my obligations to the learned Canon Cureton, for his friendly offices on these and other
occasions. I must also add that Professor Lepsius and Dr. Abeken, and the late Baron Bunscn, kindly exerted themselves
to obtain permission for my lexicon to bo printed at Berlin, at the joint expense of the Prussian Government and the Academy
of Sciences; and several of the learned Orientalists of Germany seconded their endeavours; but conditions were proposed to
me to which I could not willingly accede.

After a stay of somewhat more than seven years in Cairo, a considerable portion of which period was spent by me in
collecting and collating the principal materials from which my lexicon is composed, I returned to England; leaving to
the sheykh Ibraheem Ed-Dasookee the task of completing the transcription of those materials, a task for which he had become
fully qualified.



* Cited in page 123 of this work.



xxiv PREFACE.

I must now add some explanations necessary to facilitate the use of my lexicon.

The arrangement that I have adopted is, in its main features, the same as that of Golius : the words being placed
according to their radical letters; and the roots being arranged according to the order of their letters (commencing with the
first of those letters) in the usual alphabet.

Words of three different classes, in which the radical letters are the same, but different in number, I place in the same
article. The first of these classes consists of words of two radical letters ; as jj : the second class, of reduplicative triliteral-
radical words, in which the first and second radical letters are the same as those of the first class, and the third the same as
the second of that class ; as J^' and ji and JiJ &amp;c. : and the third class, of reduplicative quiulriliteral-radical words, in
which the first and third radical letters are the same as the first of the first class, and the second and fourth the same as the
second of that class ; as Jj^ and aJL&amp; and j(l( &amp;c. These three classes are included in the same article in all the best
Arabic lexicons ; and two reasons may be given for my following the same plan. One reason is similarity of signification.
Words of the first and second corresponding classes very seldom exhibit an alliance in signification; but instances of such
alliance in words of the first and third classes are less rare ; and instances of alliance in signification in words of the second
and third classes are very numerous. The other reason is, that such words arc generally held to be derived from the same
root. Some of the Arabian lexicologists hold that a word of the class of jj is a bilitcral-radical word ; so that the letters of
its root are represented by ** : but most of them regard it as, absolutely, a trilitcral-radical word ; so that the letters of its
root arc represented by j«j. With respect to a word such as jjb, the opinion held by El- Farm and others, and ascribed to
EI-Khalcel, is, that it is to be represented by iju*; so that the letters of its root are represented by «*: another opinion,
ascribed to El-Khalccl and his followers among the Basrces and Koofecs, is, that it is to be represented by jiJ&gt;i; so that the
letters of its root are represented by j*i : another, ascribed to Secbaweyh and his companions, is, that it is originally a word
to be represented by jJb, and that the third radical letter is changed, and made the same us the first; so that the letters of
its root arc represented by the same letters as if the word itself were to be represented by jAni' the opinion commonly
obtaining among the Basrecs is, that it is to be represented by jj&amp;; so that the letters of its root are represented, in tin's case
also, by J*» ; and as the last of these modes of representing the word is the one most usual, I generally adopt this mode
in my lexicon, except in quoting from an author who uses another mode. The triliterul root, in both of these classes
of words, is that which is preferred in the Muzhir, where, in the 40th Section, not fur from the commencement, these
different opinions arc stated.

Agreeably with the same principle, quasi-quadrilitcral-radieal words (the conjugations and varieties of which will be
found in a table inserted in this preface) I class with the triliteral-radical words from which they are derived by the Arabian
lexicologists and grammarians.

What is commonly called " the Verb of Wonder" I mention among the verbs. The Koofees say that it is a noun,
meaning an epithet. (See li^j L£»\ u, in article -JU.)

Dialectic variants, synonyms, and words nearly synonymous, from the same root, are mentioned and explained in one
paragraph : but every word thus explained in a paragraph headed by another word is also mentioned by itself, or accompanied
by a word or words nearly resembling it in form, with a reference to that paragraph. (In order to facilitate the reference, an
arrow-head (*) is inserted to render conspicuous a word explained in a paragraph headed by another word.) Several obvious
advantages result from this arrangement; not the least of which is a considerable saving of room. In these cases, when I
have found it possible to do so, I have placed the most common word first, or otherwise distinguished it from the rest:
sometimes I have shown which words are more or less common by the authorities that I have indicated for them.



PREFACE. m

When a noun is not found at the head of a paragraph, or by itself, or with another nearly resembling it in form, it is to
be looked for among the infinitive nouns, which are mentioned with their respective verbs. And plurals are to be found under
their singulars.

Words that arc regularly formed, ad libitum, (such as active and passive participial nouns, and nouns denoting the
comparative and superlative degrees, Ac.,) are not mentioned, unless for special reasons.

In respect of the places which I have assigned to arabicized words, I have generally followed the usual practice of the
Arabian lexicographers; that is, I have generally placed them as though they were derived from Arabic roots; because most
students look for them under the headings beneath which I have mentioned them, and because many of them have derivatives
formed from them in the regular Arabic manner. Bnt, properly speaking, every letter in an arabicized word is regarded by
most of the Arabian lexicologists as radical.

When several significations arc assigned to one word &amp;c, connected by "or," it is often the case that one is right in
one instance, and another in another; and not unfrequcntly, that all arc correct in different instances.

Whenever I have found it possible to do so. I have distinguished (by the mark t) what is affirmed to be tropical from
what is proper ; generally on the authority of the Asas. I have also generally distinguished (by the mark t) what I regard
as evidently, or probably, tropical, when I have found no express authority for asserting such to be the case. Thus I have
often l»ccn enabled to draw clearly what may be termed the "genealogies" of significations. Always, in the arrangement
»f significations, I have, to the utmost of my ability, paid attention to their relations, one to another. The mark — is used
to denote a break in the relations of significations &amp;c. ; and= denotes an extraordinary, or a complete, dissociation.

Numerous words in the Siluih and K.imoos and most other Arabic lexicons arc merely said to be the names of certain
plants or animals. Of these I have generally found and given explanations which have either enabled me to determine the
particular species to which they apply or may enable others to do so, and which will show that, the applications of many of
these words have been changed in post-classical times. For the names and descriptions of plants, my chief authority is
Aboo-Hanecfch Ed-Bccnawarcc, who is generally held to have adhered to the original nomenclature more accurately than
any other writer on the Arabian flora, enabled to do so in many cases by his own careful investigations, and by consulting
Arabs of the desert, at a sufficiently early period, in the third century of the Flight. I have been induced to mention the
properties commonly attributed by the Arabs to plants and drugs &amp;c, though they are generally fanciful, because they
.sometimes help to point out what is meant by an explanation otherwise vague, and sometimes elucidate far-fetched comparisons
or allusions.

The explanations of the particles are extremely defective in almost all the Arabic lexicons ; but of this very important
class of words, generally more difficult to explain than any other class, I have found, in the Mughnee, illustrations even more
ample than I required. Though I have generally omitted the statement of opinions evidently erroneous, and refuted in the
Mughnee, I have in some degree imitated the author of that work by endeavouring to treat such words rather too largely
than too scantily.

Of the learning of Golius, and the industry of Freytag, I wish to speak with sincere respect, and with gratitude for
much benefit derived by me from their works before circumstances gave me advantages which they did not enjoy. But lest
I should be charged with omitting important matters in some of the originals from which my work is composed, it is necessary
for me to state that, in countless instances, both of those lexicographers have given explanations, more or less full, as from



XXVI



PREFACE.



the Sihah or Kamoos or both, when not one word thereof, nor even an indication, is found in either of those originals:* and
that much of what Freytag has given as from the Kamoos is from the Turkish Translation of that lexicon, of which I have
before spoken, a work of considerable learning, but of no authority when no voucher is mentioned in itt I have myself
occasionally cited the Turkish Translation of the Kamoos, but only when I have not found what I wanted in any other work,
and, in a case of this kind, only when I have felt confidence in its correctness, or when I have desired a confirmation of my
own opinion. In very few instances have I adopted its explanations; having often found them to be glaringly incorrect; in
some cases, from its author's having partially misunderstood what he had to translate ; but in more cases, from his having
altogether failed to understand, and therefore having given literal renderings which are far from conveying the meanings
intended.

Proper names of persons and of places, and post-classical words and significations, I have, with very few exceptions,
excluded from my lexicon. A dictionary of words of the former class, such as would satisfy the wants of students, would of
itself alone form a large volume; for the sources from which it might be drawn arc abundant, and not difficult of access. A
dictionary of post-classical Arabic, worthy of being so called, could not be composed otherwise than by a considerable number
of students in different cities of Europe where good libraries of Arabic manuscripts arc found, and by as many students in
different countries of Asia and Africa; partly from books, and partly from information to be acquired only by intercourse with
Arabs; and several of those who should contribute to its composition would require to be well versed in the sciences of the
Muslims. In excluding almost all post-classical words and significations, I have followed the example of every one of the most
esteemed Arabian lexicographers; and the limits that I have assigned to my labours have certainly been rather too wide than
too narrow, ns will be sufficiently shown by the fact that the quantity of the matter comprised in the fust eighth part of my
First Book (l to &amp; inclusive) is treble the quantity of the corresponding portion of Frcytag's Lexicon, although I leave rare
words &amp;c. for my Second Book.

I have inserted nothing in my lexicon without indicating at least one authority for it, except interwoven additions of
my own which I have invariably distinguished by enclosing them between square brackets. Throughout Part 1 of the First
Book, I have generally made the indications of the authorities as numerous as I conveniently could; but I have not thought
it desirable to do so throughout, as these indications occupy much space, and what is most important is to note the oldest
authority mentioned in any of my originals, with one or more of good repute to confirm it. A table of the authorities inserted
in this preface will show which of them I have cited through the medium of the Tiij el-'Aroos or the ListUi cl-'Arab. Such
authorities I have often indicated without any addition.} When two or more indications of authorities arc given, it is to be
understood that they agree essentially, or mainly ; but not always that they agree in words. When any authority is, in an important
degree, less full, or less clear, than another or others by which it is accompanied, I distinguish it by an asterisk placed after the initial



• By this remark, I may perhaps provoke the retort that, in composing
an Arabic-English lexicon wholly from Arabic sources, I am myself
doing what may be resolved into something like reasoning in a circle.
But such is not the case ; for the words employed in explanations in the
Arabic lexicons arc generally still used in the senses in which they are
there employed ; and the intended meanings of words that arc not still
used in such senses arc, with few exceptions, easily determined by
examples in which they occur, or by the general consent of the learned
among the Arabs in the present day. Of the exceptional difficulties of
interpretation, I have already said enough ; and for my own sake, as
well as for the sake of truth, I by no means wish to underrate them.

t In Freytag's first volume, the authorities are seldom indicated. —



Sometimes explanations given by Golius ns from the Siluili or Kamoos or
both, and not found in cither of those works, are copied by Freytag without
his stating such to be the case, and without his indicating the authorities
or authority assigned by Golius : for example, three such instances occur
in the short article •_/,&gt;.

I In a few instances, in the Taj el-'Aroos, where its author has drawn
from the Tahdhceb or the Mohkam through the medium of the Lisan
el-'Arab, I have found the Tahdhceb erroneously named as his authority
instead of the Mohkam, or the Mohkam instead of the Tahdhceb.—
Sometimes an authority is mentioned by a surname borne by two or
more, so that the person meant is doubtful.



PREFACE. xxvii

or initials &amp;c. by which it is indicated. Frequently it happens that an explanation is. essentially the same in the Lisan
el-' Arab and the Taj cl-'Aroos, but more full, or more clear, in the former: in cases of this kind I have generally indicated
only the latter as my authority.

Sometimes I have been obliged to employ English terms which have not, to my knowledge, been used by any other
writer; but I have been careful to invent only such as will, I believe, be easily understood. For example, I have applied the
epithet "auroral" to certain risings and settings of stars or astcrisms, to denote the restriction of those risings and
settings to the whole period of the morning-twilight: the epithet "heliacal," applied to such risings, would restrict them
overmuch. Lexicological and grammatical terms employed in my lexicon will be found in one of the tables inserted in
this preface.

I have supposed the student who will make use of this work to be acquainted with the general rules of grammar. These
he must bear in mind when he meets with 'particular rules mentioned by me. For instance, from his finding it stated, in
page 77 of this lexicon, that, when *j)i is used in the sense of J^£, the noun which follows it is put in the same case as that
which precedes it, he must not imagine that exceptions to this rule are presented by such phrases as «iT ^l &lt;J1 ^ ( There is no
deity other than, i. e. but, God) and „1»U£» •$ t£i I jl C&gt; ( This is not anything but a uniting) and Jjj y\ j^.1 ^» ;£». U {No one came
but Zeyd) and ^U£» *jji /JL| \jl J4&gt; (which means the same as the second of these phrases) : for in each of these examples the
noun preceding y\ is regarded as being virtually in the same case as the noun following it. (See a note in Dc Sacy's Arabic
Grammar, 2nd ed., vol. ii. p. 404.)

Considering the size of this work, the quantity of Arabic type that it comprises, the minuteness of many of the
characters employed in it, and the excessive care required in the placing of those small characters, no student can reasonably
hope to find it entirely free from typographical faults, whether they be such as have originated from the compositors and have
escaped the scrutiny of the author, or such as are almost inevitable in the process of printing. I shall use my utmost
endeavours to detect such faults, and to note them for correction.

The following tables will, I believe, supply all further explanations that will be needed.



XXV1U PREFACE.



I.— Table of the Conjugations of Arabic Verbs.

1. (1st variety) J*, J£ , (2nd) J3, J£ : (3rd) JZ, jX : (4th) Jji, J£ , (5th) J3, J£ : (Gtb) J*, JJ£

2. J«i : variations ^li (for Jv2i) and the like.

3. JtU.

. ••••

4. J*il.

8. jft ^variations jSj, i„ the eases of verbs of which the J is O, *, ^ ,, &gt;,;, ^ ^ ^ ^ t , or * , als0 Jfc (for ^ ^ ^ ^ ;
J-A3 &amp;c. (for jJUii &amp; c .)

6. J*U3 : variations Jiui, in cases like those in which jjui sometimes becomes j%\ : also JiU3 kc. (for J^ufj &amp; c .)

7. jiLl : variations j^il (for j^Jil) and the like ; and JJut (for JJL^il) and the like.

8. J3l : variation, J&amp; ji, Ji, or J^, in dlc „*, of verbs of which thc £ j, 0&gt; ^ ^ fc fc ^ ^ ^ ^ ^ ^ fc ^ ^ ^ ^ ^ ^

(for £%, &gt;&amp; and &gt;Jj and #1 (for &gt;L S .), ££l (for £%, j£t (for J&gt;#1), &gt;} and &gt;Jj and &gt;&amp; (for #&gt;]), ftjl (for $.),
&lt;***! and j£t (for ^1), ^Lil and J^\ (for v&gt;£t), "&gt;3Uj («« *j£% £tl (for £&amp;), J#J and ^ILfcl Rnd J#| (for Jj&amp;l), J&amp;
(for ^iijl), j!5l (for jl^fl) : j&amp;| and JJel (for Jji^l).

9. Jm»\ : variations JUil, in the case of a verb of which thc J is unsound j as ^jl : and JjJiil ; as JLhyi

■• * ■»

10. J w L 7 . n l : variations clk_&gt;t and et-l (for clki*l).

- '* " '*

11. JU*I : variation JJUij, in tlic case of a verb of which thc J is unsound ; as jjjl^-t.

12. J*y6l.

13. J^ll



Q- L #* Q 2. J&amp;5. q. 3. JiSA.



Q. 4. Jjbel.



It. Q. 1. Verbs of thc classes of j£ (in which thc first and third radical letters are thc same, and thc second and fourth,) and ^^. (in which lite
third and fourth radical letters arc the same).

11. Q. 2. Verb* of the classes of JJLJ and i r '}L ~

It. Q. 3. Verbs of the class of JJJ£\.

It. Q. 4. Verbs of the class of jU^ mentioned above, (sec 9,) as variations of jiil, may be ch.sscd utidcr this head.



Q.Q.I. Ji*;^; &amp; (as o&amp; according to some, and '&amp;£). J&amp;: jfc. J^ ; j£; j£ ; j£ ; j£ : jifcj j£; j£; j£ ;

J#5 JV: Jtfj JX, J*U; j£; Jiuij JSfc
Q. Q. 2. &gt;£i£ ; J&amp;: j£j ; J^, J^: J#i ; j£S: j£3.
Q. Q. 3. [», jSfy jU,, jti,. J^j, ^, : J^, : ^
Q. Q.4. JUfc, J^Jl: Jja*,; J^|,, ^ l: ja,.

** ** * *

Beside these, there are some other forms of Q. Q. verbs, not to be classed with any of the foregoing. And probably there are some other varieties of
Q. Q. 2 ; each quasi-passive of Q. Q. 1.



PREFACE.



XXIX



II.— Table of Lexicological and Grammatical Terms #c. used in the following work.



Accord., for according.
Accub. case, for accusative case, v
Act, for active, J*ui) ^» or&gt;ji*iA).
Act. part. n.,for active participial noun, ^cM^X.
Adv. n., for adverbial noun, «j£l», and some-
times iLe; of place, J&amp; &lt;*&gt;j*i a nd of



• *t*



time, oW *-*&gt;*•
Agent, J*U.
Analogous, or regular, ^W* and wrtf*«

Analogy, l*\i.

Anomalous, or irregular, LS -»l e J ^ and ,^*»* ^

or id (sec " Dcv.") or j 3 U (see " Extr.").
Aor., for aorist, c jU&gt;-o.

Aplastic, applied to a noun and to a verb, «***» «
App., /or apparently.

Appositivc, ^13.

Attribute, or predicate, jo— « and j^.
Drokcn pl.,/or broken plural, j-X* *-»»••
Coll. gen. n., for collective generic noun, ^-1
-*4 u -— ; also called a lexicological

plural, ,*$,*) £♦». #

Complement of a ))rcfixcd noun, *JI *_JLa*.

S ' • •
Complete, t. c. attributive, verb,&gt;U J«*.

Conj., for conjugation, ^&gt;\f.

* i , , ■•»•*•#

Conjunct, Jyoy*: conjunct noun, Lr «-'l Jy*** '•
• i ■ ' .* ' •••••* '

conjunct particle, ^j»- yjyoyt.

■-' • » •• -

and oJoVt



J, or



icrm, *-



.^UjuoI. _ Conventional



Conjunction,

Contr., ./or contrary

Conventional term,
in
language, «J&gt;j«.

• *» • »-

Corroborative, ju£»U and J^=»y-

Decl., /&gt;r declinable, «_&gt;«»o : perfectly decl.,

yjj^a^, and wycu«: imperfectly decl., j*b.

, ^ * »j ^ •'

Oj_^a-&lt;&gt; and \j g0i* j&amp;.

Defective verb, i. c. having « or iC for the last
• * «•
radical letter, ^aiU cJ***

Dcv.,, /or deviating; as in the phrase, Deviating

from the constant course of sjiecch (with

respect to analogy, or rule, or with respect

2 , • *

to usage) ; ili. This term and jiU (sec
" Extr.") are often used in the lexicons in-
discriminately.
•'»
Dial., for dialect, ii).

Dial. var. of, for dialectic variant of, . J &lt;UU.

•* » *
Dim., for diminutive, j*~a-».

Enunciativc, %Jl.

Epithet, and epithctic phrase, c-j«j and oLoj

and *io.
Ex.,/&gt;r example.
Expl., for explained.
Expos., for exposition, ~.ji, and j~-i3 : the latter

particularly applied to an exposition of the

I£ur-an.
Extr.,/or extraordinary (with respect to analogy,

or rule, or with respect to usage), jjU. (See

« Dev.")
Bk. I.



Fern., for feminine, si~&gt;y».
Fnt., for future, J..i. T *. a ^

Gen. case, for genitive case, t&gt;»*». andj^
Gen. n.,/or generic noun, br ^ &gt; »wt.

Hollow verb, «-Jy»-l J«».

Homonym, i)^£~*, for a^i J)jZZ~t.

I. q.,/&gt;r idem quod.

Ideal (as opposed to real) subst, VJ i«-» ,

simply ^yii. ( ^
Imitative sequent, cUI.

• •I v.

Imperative, *•!.

Inchoative, Ijl^-«.

Incomplete, i.e. non-attributive, verb, ^aJU J«*,
. » »•» *» ' '

qtjMjJs- J*i.

Indecl.,/&gt;r indeclinable, ^^-^ *.

Inf. n., /»• infinitive noun, jjuo*. Inf. n. of

unity, S^JLI jj-ai. Inf. n. of modality,
»a •» * »

•" * ♦

Instrumental noun, &lt;UI &gt;0 -(J.

* « ,-j j»» • ■-

Intrans.,/or intransitive, jjCU^ and^^.

Irreg.,/or irregular: see "Anomalous."

Lit., /or literally.

Mahmooz verb, jvov° J***

Mansoob aor., /or mansoob aorist, v* - *'* - W

Masc, /or masculine, y=»Xe.

• • *
Measure, ££%•

* &gt; * » •
Mejzoom aor., /or mcjzoom aorist,&gt;^&gt;^-« Pj

Metaphor, 5jU^-.l.

Metaphorical, ^,Ui-»V

Metonymy, &lt;bU£a.
• •'
N., /or noun, —A

N. un.,/or noun of unity, »&gt;^.lj and «x»t&gt;

Nom. case, /or nominative case, *ij.

Objective complement of a verb, J&gt;««-» or
• *»'

Part.'n. : see "act. part, n." and " pass. part, n."

••#
Particle, «-»»»•. ,

Pass., /or passive, J y U&gt;. U ^^i-* or Jjt " - »"• Jt

Pass. jmrt. n., //r passive participial noun, ^^.1

J&gt;»^-

Perfect pi., for perfect plural, ^JU £*»- ; also
• » • • #
called a sound pi., » t * * f*"

Perfect verb, /'. ''. one which has not two radical
letters alike, nor has » nor « nor ij for one
of its radical letters, ^L- J«4. (See also
"Sound verb.")

Vers., for person (of a verb).

VI., for plural, »i».. PI. of pauc, for plural of
paucity, il» &gt;«»• PL of mult., for plural of
multitude, £&amp; £**. PI. pi., /or plural of

a plural, gU- fU-
Possessive noun or epithet (such as^»l3 and ^"9
&amp;c.), v-llil ,ji« ^^»l (a kind of relative
noun).

• ,S " i ' ' *

Post-classical, jJ^» and «_&gt;j
Predicate : see " Attribute."
Prefixed noun, JU«.



Prep., for preposition,



^Jjm-, and sometimes



Pret,/or preterite, yoU.

Prov., for proverb, Jl». s

Q.,/or quadriliteral-radical verb, ^eWj J«*. &lt;#
Q. Q-, /&gt;»• quasi-quadriliteral-radical verb, J«*
" ^i * ' \'

Q. v.^/or quod vide.

Quasi-coordinate, j « JU : see art. i&gt;*J. • #

Quasi-inf. n., for quasi-infinitive noun, ,J-a-» ^J

and jj. o « » ~w».

Quasi-pass., /&gt;r quasi-passive, pjUx«-

Quasi-pl. n.,/or quasi-plural noun, g^-^-V

Quasi-sound verb, i. e. one having jor^ for its
* ' *•
first radical letter, Jtt* J*J.

R. Q.,/or reduplicative quadriliteral-radical verb,

•' - * ' i" *i*i

Real (as opposed to ideal) subst., £** jr*\ or)

simply j&gt;U, and OliJ^or simply Ol'i.

f * * *i
Receptacular noun, V»«&gt;r*'*

Reg.,/or regular: see "Analogous."

Rel. n.,/or relative noun, w»^—u^-^, or 4-J.

Simple subst. (as opposed to inf. n.),^!.

Sing., for singular, }jk* and «x»-lj.

Sound pi., /or sound plural : see " Perfect pi."

Sound verb, t. e. one which is not of the class
termed " perfect," but which has not ^ nor
(j for one of its radical letters : or, as used
in the 'Eyn and several other lexicons, one
that has not ^ nor i_$ nor . for one of its
radical letters : L f J *$*. (Sec " Perfect
verb.")

Specificativc, or discriminative, J««&amp;

State, denotative of, JW.

Subject (as correlative of attribute or predicate),

•- &lt; • &gt;

' * . • •

Subst.,/or substantivej^o-il.
• -' '

Substitute, Jj^.

Syll. 8igns,/or syllabical signs, Jiiii.

Syn.,/or synonym and synonymous, «_»&gt;j^» and

*3i\£». Syn. with, for synonymous with,

J Hi.
Trad.,/&gt;r tradition, w»jj».

Trans., for transitive, jmi* and J»'5-
Transposition, « T Jl*. Formed by transposition,

Tropical, JWh* an " LSiV-*-
Unsound verb, t. «. one having ^or ^ for one
of its radical letters : or, as used in the 'Eyn

and several other lexicons, one having j or

%**•* •»
i&lt; or • for one of its radical letters : J-j-&gt; ^}*i.
*^ •» '

V., for verb, J*i.

• #•
Verbal noun, J*i^l.



X means asserted to be tropical.
Jt „ asserted to be doubly tropical,
f „ supposed by me to be tropical.



PKEFACE.



I II.— Chronologic al list of the more celebrated of the Lexicologists and Grammarians cited in the following work, extracted from the 48&lt;A Section of

the Muzhir : with some additions, which are marked with an asterisk.



208 or 209 or 210 or 211

. 205 or 206 or 213
. 214 or 215 or 21G



•Ibn-'Abbds: died in the year of the Flight 08

•Mujdhid : said to have lived 83 years ; and

to have died in 100 or 101 or 102 or 103

*#atadeh : born in GO : died in 117 or 118

Aboo-'Amr Ibn-El-'Ala: (*born atMckkeh,
in the year of the Flight 70 or 68 or

65 :) died in 151 (»or 154) or 159

El-Khaleel : lived to the age of 74 .... 160 or 170 or 175
•El-Leyth Ibn-Nasr Ibn-Seiyar El-Khurii-
sdnee : contemporary with, and com-
panion of, El-Khalcel.

Yoonus : born in the year 90 182 *or 183

•Ahu-d-Dukeysh: contemporary with Yoonus.

EI-Kisd-ce 182 or 183 or 189 or 192

Seebawcyh : lived 32 years, or 40 and odd

years: died in . . . 101 (»or 177) or 180 or 188 or 194

Aboo-Mohammad El-Yezeedee: lived 74

years : died in 202

En-Nadr Ibn-Shumeyl : died in 203 or 204

S"tnib 206

Et-Farra : lived 67 years 207

Aboo-'Obcydeh (*Maamar Ibn-El-Muthenna

Et-Teymoe) : born in 112: died in .
Aboo-'Amr Esh-Sheybdnce : lived 110 (*or

111) or 118 years : died in
Aboo-Zcyd(*El-Ansdrce:) lived 93 years: died in
El-Asma'ee : born in 123 (»or 122) : died in (»214 or) 215 or 216 *or 217
•El-Lihydnce: contemporary with El-Kisa-ee
and Aboo-'Obeydeh and Aboo-Zeyd and
El-Asma'ee.
Abu-1-flasan El-Akhfash . .

* Abu-1-Hey them : apreccptorof Aboo-'Obeyd.
•Ibn-Buxurj : contemporary with Abu-1-Heythem
Aboo-'Obeyd : lived 67 years : died in
Ibn-El-Aardbce : born in 150: died in
•Shemir: contemporary with Ibn-El-Aarabee.

Ibn-Es-Sikkcet ('Yaakoob) 244

Aboo-IIittim Es-Sijistanee : lived nearly 90

years : died in 248 or 250 or 254 or 255

•Ea-Sukkarco (author of an " Exposition of
the Deewdn El-Hudhaleeyeen ") : bora

in 212: died in 270 or 275

Ibn-#uteybch : [also called El-Kutabee, and
by some, (among whom is the author of
the Tdj-cl-'Aroos,) less properly, EI-
K u toy bee : (see the Biogr.Dictionary of En-

Nawawee, p. 771 :)] born in 213 : died in 267 *or 270 or 271 or 276
•Aboo-IIancefch Ed-Deenawaree (author of

the " Book of Plants ") 282

El-Mubarrad : born in 210 : died in . . . 282 or 285 *or 286

Thaalab (•Abu-l-'Abbds Ahmad Ibn-Yahya,
author of the " Fascch") : born in 200 :

died in 291

Kurds. cir. 310

Ez-Zcjjnj (•Aboo-Is-hak) 311

•Ibn-Dureyd (author of the "Jemharah"):
born in 223, or [about five years later,
for] it is said that he lived 93 years, not

more, and died in . , , 321

'Ibrahcem I bn- Mohammad Ibn-'Arafch(Nif-

taweyh) : born in 244 or 250 : died in 323



210 or 215 or 221



223 or 224 or 230
. 231 or 233



(•327 or) 328

(•337 or) 339 or 340

. . 343

. 347

. . 367

. 368

. . 370

. »370or371

(•376 or) 377



379



Aboo-Bckr Ibn-El-Ambaree : born in 271 :

died in

Ez-Zcjjiijee

•El-Farabee .......

lbn-I)urustawcyh: born in 258: died in

Ibn-El-Kootocyeh

Es-Seenifee : born before the year 270 : died in

Ibn-Khalaweyh

El-Azherco (author of the "Tahdhecb"):

•born in 282: died in

Aboo-'Alcc El-Fdriscc : (*livcd more than 90

years:) died in

Aboo-Bekr Ez-Zubeydcc (author of an abridg-
ment of the " 'Eyn" ....
•Ibn-'Abbdd (the Sahib, author of the " Mo-

hect"): born in 326: died in 385

•El-Khattiibeo 300

Ibn-Jinnce (•Abu-1-Fet-h 'Othman): born

before the year 330 : died in 392

Ibn-Faris ("390 or) 395

El-Jowharec (author of the " Sihah ") . . . »393 or 397 or 398

El-IIarawcc (author of the " Gharccbeyn ") 401

•Mohammad Ibn-Jaafar El-Kazzaz 412

El-Jawaleckcc 425

•Ibn-Et-Tciyancc (author of the "Moo'ab") 43G

Ibn-Secdch ('author of the "Mohkam"):

lived about GO years : died in 458

El-Khatccb Et-Tcbrcczcc : born in 421: died in 502

*Er-Itaghib El-Isfahanec : died in the early
part of century five.

Ibn-El-Kattsia : born in 433: died in 515

•EI-Mcydance: died in 513

Ibn-Es-Sccd El-Batalyowscc : born in 444:

died in 521

Ez-Zamakhsherce (•author of the " 'Asds" and

" Keshsbaf," &amp;c.) : born in 467 : died in 538

•Es-Suhcylee (author of the " Ilowd") 581

Ibn-Barree ('author of " Annotations on the

Sihah") . . 582

•Ibn-El-Atheer El-Jezeree, (Mcjd-ed-Deen,

author of the " Nihdych ") 606

•El-Fakhr Er-Razee GOO

•El-Mutarrizee (author of the " Mughrib ") :

born in 536 : died in G10

Es-Saghanec (*or Es-Saghanee, author of the
'"Obdb" and of the " Tekmileh fi-s-

Sihdh ") : born in 577 : died in 660

Er-Radce Esh-Shdtibee : born in 601 : died in ... 684

•El-Beyddwee 685 or 690 or 691

El-Jcmdl Ibn-Mdlik : born in 600 : died in 692

•Ibn-Mukarram (author of the "Lisdn

el-' Arab "): born in 630 : died in 711

•El-Fciyoomee (author of the " Misbdli,"
which he finished in 734).

Aboo-Heiydn : born in 654 : died in 745

•Ibn-Hisham (author of the "Mughnee"):

born in 708 : died in 761 or 762

El-Feyrooadbadee (author of the " £dmoos "

•and the" Basdi'r"): born in 729: died in . . . .816
•The seyyid Murtada Ez-Zebeedee (author of

the"TajekAroos"): died in 1205



PREFACE.



XXXI




IV. — Indications of Autlioritie*.

From all these authorities I have drawn through the medium of the Taj el-'Aroos or the Lisan el-'Arab, except those
distinguished by the mark J, which denotes those whence I have always drawn immediately : from many of them I have also
drawn through the medium of some other lexicon than the two above named : and from those distinguished by the mark 1 1 have
often, or generally, drawn immediately. What is meant by an asterisk placed after any indication of an authority in my lexicon
has been explained in page xxvi.

Jm, The " Jemharah " of Ibn-Dureyd.

+K, The " Kamoos."

KI, The kddee Mydd. .

t KL, The " Kenz cl-Loghah," of Ibn-Maaroof ; an Arabic-Persian

Dictionary.

J KT, The " Kitab et-Taarcefat."

Kf, The " Kifayet el-Mutahaffidh."

Kh El-Khaleel, commonly supposed to be the author of the
« 'Eyn."

|Kr, Kurda, author of the " Munjid."

Ks, El-Ki'sd-ee.

fKsh, The " Kcshshaf " of Ez-Zainakhsherce.

Kt, El-Kuteybce.

Ktr, Kutrub.

J Kull, the " Kullccyiit " of Abu-1-Baka.

+Kur, The " Kur-an."

Kz, El-Kazzdz.

-tKzw, El-Kazwcenee.

+L, The'" Lisan el-'Arab."

Lb, El-Lcblec.

Lh, El-Li hyiince.

Lth El-Lc'yth Ibn-Nasr Ibn-Scivdr, held by El-Azhcrce to be Uie
author of the'" 'Eyn," which he calls " Kitab Lcyth."

+M, The " Mohkam."

J M A The " Mukaddamet el-Adab " of Ez-Zamakhshercc

fMF, Mohammad lbn-Et-Teiyib El-Fdsec, author of "Annotations

on the Kdmoos."

fMS, The " Mukhtur cs-Sihah."

Mbr, El-Mubarrad.

tMeyd, El-Mcyddnee's " Proverbs."

tMgh. The " Mughrib " of El-Mutarrizec.

Mf, The " Mujmal " of Ibn-Faris.

tMsb, The " Misbdh " of El-Feiyoomec.

fMtr, El-Mutarrizec, author of the " Mughrib. "
tMiighnec, The " Miighni-l-Lebceb " of Ibn-Hishdm.

tMz,° The " Muzhir " of Es-Suyootcc.

Nh, Tlic "Nihaych" of Ibn-El-Athcer El-Jezorec (Mcjd cd-

Decn).
Ns, En-Ncsa-cc.

( ), The " 'Obab " of Es-Saghance.
t PS, The " Persian Translation of the Sihah."

It,' The " Rowd " (" Er-Rowd cl-Unuf ") of Es-Suheylcc.

fS,' Tlic " Sihah."

JSM, The seyyid Murtada, author of the " Taj cl-'Aroos.

8b, Seebaweyh.

Seer, Es-Seerdfce. , . , , _ , ...

S"h, Es-Sn&lt;'hancc, author of the " 'Obab" and of the " Tckmikh

' fi-s-Sihah."
Sll, Shemir. , . „.

tSkr, Es-Sukkarcc, author of an " Exposition ot the Dccwan ti-

ll udhalccveen."
Suh", Es-Suhcylce, author of the " Rowd."

fT, The " Tahdhecb " of El-Azhcrec.

IT A, The " Taj cl-'Aroos."

JTK, The " Turkish Translation of the Kamoos."

TS, The " Tekmileh fi-s-Sihah " of Es-Saghance.

tT'f, The " Tahdhecb et-Tahdhceb."

Th, Thaalab, author of the "Faseeh." ,«., ,, „

fW, El-Wahidee's " Exposition of the Deewan of El-Mulanebbce,

edited by Dr. Dietcrici.
Yoo, Yoonus.

Yz, El-Yczcedce.

fZ, Ez-Zamakhsherce.

Zbd, Ez-Zubeydee, author of an " Abridgment of the Eyn.

+Zj, Ez-Zejjaj.



tJM,

JJcl,

































































































+A, 						   The " Asds " of Ez-Zamakhshcree.
AA,						   Aboo-'Ainr Ibn-El-'Ala, and Aboo-'Amr Esh-Sheybánee : each being cited simply by the name of" Aboo-'Amr."
AAF, 						   Aboo-'Alce El-Farisee.
ADk,						   Abu-d-Dukeysh.
AHat, 						   Aboo-IIdtim Es-Sijistance.
AHei						   Aboo-Heiyán.
AHeyth 						   Abu-l-Heythem.
AHn						   Aboo-Hancefch Ed-Dccnawarcc, author of the "Book of Plants."
+AM						   Aboo-MaiiHoor (same as Az).
AO						   Aboo-'Obeydeh.
A'Obeyd						   Aboo-'Obeyd.
AZ						   Aboo-Zeyd.
Aal 						   El-Aalam.
Akh						   Kl-Akhfash.
As						   El-Asma'ee.
+Az						   El-Azheree (same as AM), author of the "Tahdhecb."
B 						   The " Basdir," by the author of the " Kdmoos."
+Bd 						   El-Bcyddwcc's " Exposition of the Kur-an."
Bkh						   El-Bukharec.
Btl						   El-Batalyowsce.
CK 						   The Calcutta edition of the "Kdmoos."
Dmr						   Ed-Demeree.
EM						   The "Exposition of the Mo'allakat," printed at Calcutta.
F						   El-Feyroozabadee, author of the " Kamoos."
Fei 						   El-Feiyoomee, author of the " Misbah."
Fr 						   El-Farra.
Fs						   The " Fi.seeh" of Tbaalab.
Ham 						   The " Exposition of the Hamasah," (" Hamasa; Carmina,") mi, by Kt-Tebrcezce.
Har		   				   El-Hareree's " Makdmdt," the Commentary on ; 2nd edit of Paris.
Hr 						   El-Harawee.
IAar						   llm-Kl-Aardbcc.
I'Ab						   Ibn-'Abbd*.
						   Ibn-'Akeers"Ex|iositionofthc Alfccych of Ibn-Mdhk," edited
					   Fr,
					   by Dr. Dictcrici.
					   Ilm-KI-Aiiihiircc.
					   lbn-El-Atheer El-Jezcrcc, (Mejd-cd-Dcen,) author of tlie
					   tHam,
					   "Nihaych."
					   Ibn-Barreo, author of the "Annotations on the Sihah," with

					   El-Bustec.
lAnr, 						   Ibn-Durcyd, author of the " Jemharah" &amp;c.
						   Ibn-Durustaweyh.
I'Ah, 						   Ibn-lYiris, author of the "Mujmal."
						   Ibu-llisham, author of the " Mughncc."
Jl'Ak, 						   Ibn-.Iinnce.
						   Ihii-Klnilawcyh.
I A in b, 					   Ibn-El-Koojeeyeh.
						   Ibn-Kutcybch.
I All., 					   Ibn-Kl-Kattda.
						   Ibn-Mukarram, (commonly called in the Taj cl-'Aroos " Ibn-
IB,
						   Mandhoor,") author of the " Lisan el-'Arab."
tTDrd, 						   Ibn-'Odeys.
1 Dnt, 						   tTDrd,
IF, 						   Ibn-Secdeh, author of the " Mohkam."
						   Ibn-Slmmcyl (En-Nadr).
tlllsl., 					   Ibn-Es-Sikkcet (Yaakoob).
						   Ibrahecm Ed-Dasookce.
IJ, 						   El-.Iowharcc, author of the " Sihdh."
						   IJ,
1Kb, 						   A MS. supposed to be the " Jdmi'" of El-Karmdnee: a lexicon
IKoot, 						   founded upon the "'Eyn," with additions from the
IKt, 						   " Tckmilet cl-'Eyn " of El-Khdrzcnjee.
IKtt, 						   The " Jdmi' " of the seyyid Mohammad.
tIM, 						   The " Exposition of the" ]£ur-dn " by the Jeldleyn.
														 tIM,
10,
tI8d, 														 10,
														 tI8d,
ISh,
														 ISh,
ISk,
														 ISk,
JlbrD,
														 JlbrD,
+J,
JJK, 														 +J,
xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx												 JJK,
												 xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx










XXXII



PREFACE.



I have now, to the best of my ability, supplied all the necessary apparatus for the use of my lexicon, except, only, such
information as I suppose the student to have acquired from other sources.

The Arabic title ^&gt;-UJl jU (which the Arabs in general, in the present day, the learned as well as the unlearned, would
pronounce "Medd el-Kamoos," as they deem it pedantic to pronounce the titles of books in the classical manner,) I have
adopted in imitation of that given to his lexicon by EI-Feyroozabddee. It has two meanings: "The Flow of the Sea" and
" The Extension of the Kamoos."

Not only the main expenses incurred in the composition of this work, but also the cost of the printing, and that of the
Arabic type, have been defrayed by the munificence of His Grace the Duke of Northumberland. The Arabic characters have
often been considerably altered by the Arabs themselves and by other Easterns; and still more by Europeans, to adapt them to
the purpose of printing. For this purpose, I have myself innovated a modification of one medial form and one final form,
and r . My Nephew, Mr. Edward Stanley Poole, who possesses unusual skill in Arabic caligraphy, designed, under my
superintendence, the whole of the Arabic type employed for this work ; and has also assisted me occasionally in the collation of
the proofs, previously to my own examination and correction of them; and often in other affairs connected with the printing
of my lexicon.



E. W. L.
December, 1802.






A calamity that has recently befallen me, in common with multitudes of other persons, — the decease of the Illustrious Duke
by whom this work was originated, and whose munificence has constantly supplied the chief means of its support, — requires me
to announce that the event so widely and deeply deplored will not cause any interruption of the publication.

His princely patronage, granted spontaneously, and with a kindness and delicacy not to be surpassed, has l)een continued
during nearly a quarter of a century. The carrying-out of his intentions, with respect to my Lexicon, now devolves upon
His Widow, Her Grace the Duchess of Northumberland, by her own particular desire.

The intense interest that has ever been felt by Her Grace in all the great deeds whereby the departed Duke has
established countless claims upon the gratitude of his country is well known ; and it is, to me, a source of the utmost thankfulness
and pride that my own undertaking is included among the objects that have been honoured by the patronage, and stamped
with the approval, of them both.



E. W. L.



March, 1865.



POSTSCRIPT TO THE PREFACE.



Since the publication of the foregoing Preface, two occurrences have induced me to append to it this Postscript,
without waiting for the completion of my work.

The first of these occurrences was my receiving the unexpected information that the copy of the 'Obdb which I
had sought, without success, to discover in Cairo had been found and purchased, had been brought to London, and
was offered to me for sale. A most exorbitant price was demanded of me for it, and refused by me : but my late
lamented Patron, by means of a person employed to treat for it by my Nephew Mr. Reginald Stuart Poole, bought it,
for a sum which, though large, was not greater than that which I would myself willingly have paid for it if I had been
a man of wealth ; and most kindly entrusted it to me, for my use during the progress of the printing of my Lexicon.

The 'Obdb is, as I supposed it to be, and as I have since found to be stated by Hdjjee Khalecfeh, composed in
the order of the Sihah, ending in article ^ ; so that its author completed a little more than three fourths of his
intended work. To what he has borrowed from the Sihah, which he ha* freely and literally copied throughout the
'Obdb, but usually without acknowledgment, he has made large additions, with duo acknowledgments, chiefly from
the Jcmharah of Ibn-Durcyd and the Mohcct of Ibn-' Abbdd. Whether his less numerous additions be from the
original sources or from citations in other lexicons, I have not been able to determine. Of all the lexicons of earlier
authors his work most resembles the Mohkam ; which, though it is in my opinion decidedly superior to the 'Obdb in
critical accuracy and in other respects, ho seems to have strangely neglected; thereby suggesting to the author of
the Kdmoos the project of composing the Ldmi', and subsequently the composition of the Kdmoos itself.' In a notice
of its author and of his other works, in article ^ in the Tdj el-'Aroos, the 'Obdb is said to be « in twenty volumes;
and the same is said by Hdjjec Khalecfeh : but the copy of it mentioned above is in ten large quarto volumes, written
iu a very lar-o hand, and generally with all the vowel-signs and the like that are absolutely requisite. Several
portions of it°, not, however, amounting to much in proportion to the rest, had been lost when it was brought to
England : but as the work was never completed, this is less to be regretted than it would be otherwise. In many
parts it has been injured by worms ; and in some parts, by larger vermin. In other respects, it is in good preserva-
tion. I have often found it very useful in the cases of doubtful passages in the Tdj el-Aroos ; and not unfrcqucntly
in its affording me valuable additions to the contents of the latter work, though notes in its margins in the hand-
writing of thc°Scyyid Murtada show that he consulted it with much careful and critical consideration.

The second reason for my appending here this Postscript to my Preface is to correct the dates of the birth and
death of El-Azhcree. The paragraph relating to his Lexicon, the "Tahdheeb," I had inserted in its right relative
place ; but I was afterwards led to transpose it, while the Preface was in type, by observing that the place was
inconsistent with the dates of his birth and death which I had there given on the authority of two most excellent
copies of the Muzhir and had repeated in another page ; and I did not discover that these dates were incorrect until
it was too late to rectify the mistakes otherwise than by reprinting two leaves, after the Preface had been published.
El-Azheree, as is stated by Ibn-Khillikan, was born in the year of the Plight 282 ; and died in the latter part of 370,



• Throughout Part V. of my Lexicon, I have generally endeavoured to show (by the indications of my authorities) the degrees in which the
'Obdb haa borrowed from the contents of the Sihah and contributed to the contents of the £amoos.



XXX1Y



POSTSCRIPT TO THE PREFACE.



or as some say, 371 ; so that he liyed 88 or 89 years (lunar reckoning). In the year 811, heing then about 20 years
old, he became a pnsoner among the Karmatees, felling to the lot of a party of Arabs of the Desert. Among these
people he appears to have remained several years ; for he is related to have mentioned las having passed two winters
with them a Es-Samman, but usually to have wintered with them in the Dahna. And while wandering and
sojourning with them in these and other parts of Central and Northern Arabia, he collected many words and
phrases, winch he has mentioned in his Lexicon ; but expressly distinguishing them as having been heart by him
from the Arabs or from Arabs of the Desert (in both eases meaning the same) or as having been heard by him in the
Desert, lest he should be supposed to claim for them less questionable authority. His opinion of these additions to
the Tahdheeb is shown by his insertion of them, and also by a citation from a statement in his own handwriting
that m the speech of the people among whom he was in captivity, themselves Arabs of the Desert, a gross inaccuracy
or nustakc was seldom or never found. Thus we learn a very important fact respecting the gradual corruption of
the dialects of Arabic : the utmost that can be said of the dialect spoken by the wandering tribes more than nine
centuries ago in the North-Central region, where the vernacular language has continued to the present day to bo least
exposed to foreign influences and therefore least affected thereby, is, that it was free from gross inaccuracies. That
the language of the settled inhabitants throughout Arabia had long before become too much corrupted for their words
or phrases to be cited in lexicons,. unless for the purpose of discriminating them as post-classical, is admitted and
nfhrmed by all the lexicologist, who have had occasion to mention the subject: but the language now spoken in the
towns of the North-Central region (which language is well known by reason of that region's being still traversed by
one ol the great pilgrim-routcs and often visited by learned men from Egypt and from Syria) is said to be less corrupt
than arc the dialects of tho Bcdawccs of the same and of other parts.

More than seventeen hundred printed pages of my Lexicon arc now before me; and when it is considered
that this portion comprises about thrice as much matter as the corresponding portion (one half) of Frcytae's
unabridged Lexicon, I hope that the time which the printing has occupied will not be thought unreasonably'lon^.
Notwithstanding the time and pains that I have devoted to the scrutiny necessary for the detection and correction of
typographical and other errors, the errata that I have since casually observed and noted down arc not so few as I
hoped and expected them to bo : but I have generally found them to be such as any one qualified to make a pro-
litablc use of my work may easily discover and rectify without my aid.



December, 18G9.



E. W. L.
</preface>
